<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Civil War Generals</string>

    <string name="hello_world">Civil War Generals</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="union">Union</string>
    <string name="confederate">Confederate</string>
    <string name="all">All</string>
    <string name="infobutton">Help</string>
    <string name="info">Civilwargenerals contains facts and history of all generals of the US Civil War.  There is a page for every general, hundreds of images and a searchable database.  The Pictures button allows you to scroll through a long list of generals.  The three text boxes, and their triggering Search button, search the database of text associated wth every general.  You may fill in any or all three text boxes.  Search terms are <b>NOT</b> case-sensitive.  Please <b>DO NOT</b> use quotes because search phrases are automatically quoted (assumed to be exact).  For example if you enter into the three text boxes:\n\n<b>killed</b>\n<b>at night</b>\n<b>shiloh</b>\n\n...and hit the Search button, it will retrieve the 2 generals that have all three of those exact phrases somewhere on the page for the general.  Search rules are simple but not as easy as Google.  As another example, if you want to find all of the carriers that have both of the words <b>ship</b> and <b>sunk</b> anywhere, then you would <b>NOT</b> search in the first box for this\n\n<b>ship sunk</b>\n\n...as you would on Google.  Instead you will want to put one term by itself in one of the three search boxes, like this\n\n<b>ship</b>\n<b>sunk</b>\n\nPutting both words into one search box will search for the exact phrase <b>ship sunk</b>, and in this example, will return zero results.  Separate boxes will yield eleven results for this ship and sunk example.  Word fragments work and so <b>183</b> will find generals with any reference to a year in the 1830s.\nAll text and imagery are under the license found here: en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Text_of_Creative_Commons_Attribution&#8211;ShareAlike_3.0_Unported_License\nAll thanks go to civil war enthusiasts everywhere and to the wiki editors who wrote the information found here.  There are errors and omissions in this data.  Get the most accurate and up to date information here en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Civil_War\n</string>
    <string name="general">General</string>
    <string name="backbutton">back</string>
    <string name="nextbutton">next</string>
    <string name="backbuttonten">back 10</string>
    <string name="nextbuttonten">next 10</string>
    <string name="picturename">General</string>
    <string name="viewgeneral">View General</string>
    <string name="searchhint">single word, or exact phrase, no quotes, case insensitive</string>
    <string name="searchforcarriers">Search</string>
    <string name="pictures">Pictures</string>
    <string name="civilwar">\n<b> American Civil War \n</b>\n\nFrom Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia\nAmerican Civil War\n         April 12, 1861 _ May 9, 1865 (by declaration)[1]\nDate     (4 years, 3 weeks and 6 days)\n         (last_shot_fired June 22, 1865)\nLocation Southern_United_States, Northeastern_United_States, Western_United_States, Atlantic\n         Ocean\n         Union victory\n             * Slavery abolished\nResult       * Territorial_integrity preserved\n             * Lincoln_assassinated five days after Lee\'s surrender\n             * Destruction and dissolution of the Confederacy\n             * Beginning of the Reconstruction_Era\nBelligerents\n United     Confederate_States\nStates\nCommanders and leaders\nAbraham\nLincoln\nUlysses_S.  Jefferson_Davis\nGrant       Robert_E._Lee\nWilliam_T.  Joseph_E._Johnston\nSherman     Stonewall_Jackson\nGeorge_B.   Raphael_Semmes\nMcClellan   and_others\nDavid\nFarragut\nand_others\nStrength\n2,100,000   1,064,000\nCasualties and losses\n112,000\nkilled in\naction/died\nof wounds\n[2][3]\n25,000 dead 75,000_94,000 killed in action/died of wounds[2] 26,000_31,000 dead in Union\nin          prisons[3]\nConfederate ~260,000 total dead\nprisons[2]  137,000+ wounded\n365,000\ntotal dead\n[4]\n282,000\nwounded[3]\nTotal estimated 625,000&#8211;850,000 dead[5]\n    * v\n    * t\n    * e\nTheaters of the American Civil\nWar\n    * Union_blockade\n    * Eastern\n    * Western\n    * Lower_Seaboard\n    * Trans&#8211;Mississippi\n    * Pacific_Coast\nThe American Civil War, widely known in the United_States as simply the Civil\nWar as well as other sectional_names, was a civil_war fought from 1861 to 1865\nto determine the survival of the Union or independence for the Confederacy.\nAmong the 34 states as of January 1861, seven Southern slave_states\nindividually declared their secession from the United States and formed the\nConfederate_States_of_America, known as the \"Confederacy\" or the \"South\". They\ngrew to include eleven states, and although they claimed thirteen states and\nadditional western territories, the Confederacy was never diplomatically\nrecognized by a foreign country. The states that remained loyal and did not\ndeclare secession were known as the \"Union\" or the \"North\". The war_had_its\norigin in the fractious issue of slavery, especially the extension of slavery\ninto the western territories.[N_1] After four years of combat that left over\n600,000 Union and Confederate soldiers dead and destroyed much of the South\'s\ninfrastructure, the Confederacy collapsed and slavery was abolished. Then began\nthe Reconstruction and the processes of restoring national unity and\nguaranteeing civil rights to the freed slaves.\nIn the 1860_presidential_election, Republicans, led by Abraham_Lincoln, opposed\nthe expansion of slavery into U.S._territories. The Republican Party, dominant\nin the North, secured a majority of the electoral votes, and Lincoln was\nelected the first Republican president, but before his_inauguration on March 4,\n1861, seven slave states with cotton&#8211;based economies formed the Confederacy.\nThe first six to secede had the highest proportions of slaves in their\npopulations, a total of 48.8 percent for the six.[6] Outgoing Democratic President\nJames_Buchanan and the incoming Republicans rejected secession as illegal.\nLincoln\'s_inaugural_address declared his administration would not initiate\ncivil_war. Eight remaining slave states continued to reject calls for\nsecession. Confederate forces seized numerous federal forts within territory\nclaimed by the Confederacy. A peace_conference failed to find a compromise, and\nboth sides prepared for war. The Confederates assumed that European countries\nwere so dependent on \"King_Cotton\" that they would intervene; none did and none\nrecognized the new Confederate States of America.\nHostilities began on April 12, 1861, when Confederate forces fired upon Fort\nSumter, a key fort held by Union troops in South_Carolina. Lincoln called for\nevery state to provide troops to retake the fort; consequently, four more slave\nstates joined the Confederacy, bringing their total to eleven. Lincoln soon\ncontrolled the border_states, after arresting state legislators and suspending\nhabeas_corpus,[7] ignoring the ruling of the Supreme_Court\'s_Chief_Justice that\nsuch suspension was unconstitutional, and established a naval_blockade that\ncrippled the southern economy. The Eastern_Theater was inconclusive in\n1861_62. The autumn 1862 Confederate campaign into Maryland (a Union state)\nended with Confederate retreat at the Battle_of_Antietam, dissuading British\nintervention.[8] To the west, by summer 1862 the Union destroyed the\nConfederate river navy, then much of their western armies, and the Union siege\nof_Vicksburg split the Confederacy in two at the Mississippi_River. In 1863,\nRobert_E._Lee\'s Confederate incursion north ended at the Battle_of_Gettysburg.\nLincoln issued the Emancipation_Proclamation, which made ending slavery a war\ngoal.[9] Western successes led to Ulysses_S._Grant\'s command of all Union\narmies in 1864. In the Western_Theater, William_T._Sherman drove east to\ncapture Atlanta and marched_to_the_sea, destroying Confederate infrastructure\nalong the way. The Union marshaled the resources and manpower to attack the\nConfederacy from all directions, leading to the protracted Siege_of_Petersburg.\nThe besieged Confederate army eventually abandoned Richmond, seeking to regroup\nat Appomattox_Court_House, though there they found themselves surrounded by\nunion forces. This led to Lee\'s surrender to Grant on April 9, 1865. All\nConfederate generals surrendered by that summer.\nThe American Civil War was one of the earliest true industrial_wars. Railroads,\nthe telegraph, steamships, and mass&#8211;produced weapons were employed extensively.\nThe mobilization of civilian factories, mines, shipyards, banks, transportation\nand food supplies all foreshadowed World_War_I. It remains the deadliest war in\nAmerican_history, resulting in the deaths of an estimated 750,000 soldiers and\nan undetermined number of civilian_casualties.[N_2] One estimate of the death\ntoll is that ten percent of all Northern males 20_45 years old, and 30\npercent of all Southern white males aged 18_40 died.[11] From 1861 to 1865\nabout 620,000 soldiers lost their lives.[12]\n\n<u> Contents \n</u>\n\n    * 1_Causes_of_secession\n          o 1.1_Slavery\n          o 1.2_States\'_rights\n          o 1.3_Sectionalism_and_cotton_trade\n                # 1.3.1_Protectionism\n                # 1.3.2_Slave_power_and_free_soil\n          o 1.4_Territorial_crisis\n          o 1.5_National_elections\n                # 1.5.1_Nationalism_and_honor\n                # 1.5.2_Lincoln\'s_election\n    * 2_Secession_and_war_begins\n          o 2.1_Resolves_and_developments\n                # 2.1.1_Secession_of_South_Carolina\n                # 2.1.2_Secession_winter\n          o 2.2_States_align\n                # 2.2.1_Confederate_states\n                # 2.2.2_Union_states\n                # 2.2.3_Border_states\n          o 2.3_Beginning_the_war\n                # 2.3.1_Lincoln\'s_policy\n                # 2.3.2_Battle_of_Fort_Sumter\n    * 3_War\n          o 3.1_Mobilization\n                # 3.1.1_Motivation\n                # 3.1.2_Prisoners\n          o 3.2_Naval_war\n                # 3.2.1_Union_blockade\n                      # 3.2.1.1_Modern_navy_evolves\n                      # 3.2.1.2_Blockade_runners\n                      # 3.2.1.3_Economic_impact\n                # 3.2.2_Rivers\n          o 3.3_Eastern_theater\n          o 3.4_Western_theater\n          o 3.5_Trans&#8211;Mississippi\n          o 3.6_End_of_war\n                # 3.6.1_Conquest_of_Virginia\n                # 3.6.2_Confederacy_surrenders\n    * 4_Diplomacy\n    * 5_Victory_and_aftermath\n          o 5.1_Results\n          o 5.2_Costs\n          o 5.3_Emancipation\n                # 5.3.1_Issue_of_Slavery_During_the_War\n                # 5.3.2_Emancipation_Proclamation\n          o 5.4_Texas_v._White\n          o 5.5_Reconstruction\n    * 6_Memory_and_historiography\n          o 6.1_Lost_Cause\n          o 6.2_Beardian_historiography\n          o 6.3_Civil_War_commemoration\n    * 7_See_also\n    * 8_References\n    * 9_Further_reading\n    * 10_External_links\n\n<u> Causes of secession \n</u>\n\nMain articles: Origins_of_the_American_Civil_War, Timeline_of_events_leading_to\nthe_American_Civil_War and History_of_the_United_States\nThe causes of the Civil War were complex and have been controversial since the\nwar began. The issue has been further complicated by historical_revisionists,\nwho have tried to offer a variety of reasons for the war.[13] Slavery was the\ncentral source of escalating political tension in the 1850s. The Republican\nParty was determined to prevent any spread of slavery, and many Southern\nleaders had threatened secession if the Republican candidate, Lincoln, won the\n1860_election. After Lincoln had won without carrying a single Southern state,\nmany Southern whites felt that disunion had become their only option, because\nthey felt as if they were losing representation, which hampered their ability\nto promote pro&#8211;slavery acts and policies.[14]\n\n<i> Slavery \n</i>\n\nMain article: Slavery_in_the_United_States\nThe slavery issue was primarily about whether the system of slavery was an\nanachronistic evil that was incompatible with Republicanism_in_the_United\nStates, or a state&#8211;based property system compatible with and protected by the\nConstitution, as had been the case in_the_Roman_Republic.[15] The strategy of\nthe anti&#8211;slavery forces was containment _ to stop the expansion and thus put\nslavery on a path to gradual extinction.[16] To slave holding interests in the\nSouth, this strategy was perceived as infringing upon their Constitutional\nrights.[17] Slavery was being phased out of existence in the North, where\nColoured men had in some cases been granted the franchise or even_served_as\nrepresentatives; it was fading in the border_states and urban areas, but was\nexpanding in highly profitable cotton districts of the south.\nAn 1863 photo of Gordon, distributed in the North during the war.[18]\nDespite compromises in 1820 and 1850, the slavery issues exploded in the 1850s.\nCauses include controversy over admitting Missouri as a slave state in 1820,\nthe acquisition_of_Texas as a slave state in 1845 and the status of slavery in\nwestern territories won as a result of the Mexican_American_War and the\nresulting Compromise_of_1850.[19] Following the U.S. victory over Mexico,\nNortherners attempted to exclude slavery from conquered territories in the\nWilmot_Proviso; although it passed the House, it failed in the Senate. Northern\n(and British) readers recoiled in anger at the horrors of slavery as described\nin the novel and play Uncle_Tom\'s_Cabin (1852) by abolitionist Harriet_Beecher\nStowe.[20][21] Irreconcilable disagreements over slavery ended the Whig and\nKnow_Nothing political parties, and later split the Democratic_Party between\nNorth and South, while the new Republican_Party angered slavery interests by\ndemanding a definite end to its expansion. Most observers believed that without\nexpansion slavery would eventually die out; Lincoln argued this in 1845 and\n1858.[22][23]\nMeanwhile, the South of the 1850s saw an increasing number of slaves leave the\nborder_states through sale, manumission and escape. During this same period,\nslave&#8211;holding border states had more free African&#8211;Americans and European\nimmigrants than the lower South, which increased Southern fears that slavery\nwas threatened with rapid extinction in this area.[24] With tobacco and cotton\nwearing out the soil, the South believed it needed to expand slavery.[25] Some\nadvocates for the Southern states argued in favor of reopening the\ninternational slave trade to populate territory that was to be newly opened to\nslavery.[26] Southern demands for a slave code to ensure slavery in the\nterritories repeatedly split the Democratic_Party between North and South by\nwidening margins.[27][N_3]\nTo settle the dispute over slavery expansion, Abolitionists and proslavery\nelements sent their partisans into Kansas, both using ballots and bullets. In\nthe 1850s, a miniature civil war in Bleeding_Kansas led pro&#8211;South Presidents\nFranklin_Pierce and James_Buchanan to attempt a forced admission of Kansas as a\nslave state through vote fraud.[32] The 1857 Congressional rejection of the\npro&#8211;slavery Lecompton_Constitution was the first multi&#8211;party solid&#8211;North vote,\nand that solid vote was anti&#8211;slavery to support the democratic majority voting\nin the Kansas Territory.[33] Violence on behalf of Southern honor reached the\nfloor of the Senate in 1856 when a Southern Congressman, Preston_Brooks,\nphysically assaulted Republican Senator Charles_Sumner when he ridiculed\nprominent slaveholders as pimps for slavery.[34]\nThe earlier political party structure failed to make accommodation among\nsectional differences. Disagreements over slavery caused the Whig and \"Know&#8211;\nNothing\" parties to collapse. In 1860, the last national political party, the\nDemocratic_Party, split along sectional lines. Anti&#8211;slavery Northerners\nmobilized in 1860 behind moderate Abraham Lincoln because he was most likely to\ncarry the doubtful western states. In 1857, the Supreme Court\'s Dred_Scott\ndecision ended the Congressional compromise for Popular Sovereignty in Kansas.\nAccording to the court, slavery in the territories was a property right of any\nsettler, regardless of the majority there. Chief Justice Taney\'s decision said\nthat slaves were \"&#8230; so far inferior that they had no rights which the white\nman was bound to respect\". The decision overturned the Missouri_Compromise,\nwhich banned slavery in territory north of the 36Â°30\' parallel.[35]\nMembers of slave&#8211;owning planter_aristocracy dominated society and politics in\nthe South.\nRepublicans denounced the Dred Scott decision and promised to overturn it;\nAbraham Lincoln warned that the next Dred Scott decision could threaten the\nNorthern states with slavery. The Republican party platform called slavery \"a\nnational evil\", and Lincoln believed it would die a natural death if it were\ncontained.[36] The Democrat Stephen A. Douglas developed the Freeport_Doctrine\nto appeal to North and South. Douglas argued, Congress could not decide either\nfor or against slavery before a territory was settled. Nonetheless, the anti&#8211;\nslavery majority in Kansas could stop slavery with its own local laws if their\npolice laws did not protect slavery introduction.[37] Most 1850 political\nbattles followed the arguments of Lincoln and Douglas, focusing on the issue of\nslavery expansion in the territories.[22]\nBut political debate was cut short throughout the South with Northern\nabolitionist John_Brown\'s 1859 raid at Harpers_Ferry_Armory in an attempt to\nincite slave_insurrections. The Southern political defense of slavery\ntransformed into widespread expansion of local militias for armed defense of\ntheir \"peculiar\" domestic institution.[38] Lincoln\'s assessment of the\npolitical issue for the 1860 elections was that, \"This question of Slavery was\nmore important than any other; indeed, so much more important has it become\nthat no other national question can even get a hearing just at present.\"[N_4]\nThe Republicans gained majorities in both House and Senate for the first time\nsince the 1856 elections, they were to be seated in numbers that Lincoln might\nuse to govern, a national parliamentary majority even before pro&#8211;slavery House\nand Senate seats were vacated.[41] Meanwhile, Southern Vice President,\nAlexander_Stephens, in the Cornerstone_Speech, declared the new confederate\n\"Constitution has put at rest forever all the agitating questions relating to\nour peculiar institutions_African slavery as it exists among us_the proper\nstatus of the negro in our form of civilization. This was the immediate cause\nof the late rupture and present revolution.\"[42] The Republican administration\nenacted the Confiscation_Acts that set conditions for emancipation of slaves\nprior to the official proclamation of emancipation.[43] Likewise, Lincoln had\npreviously condemned slavery and called for its \"extinction.\"[44]\nConsidering the relative weight given to causes of the Civil War by\ncontemporary actors, historians such as Chandra Manning argue that both Union\nand Confederate fighting soldiers believed that slavery caused the Civil War.\nUnion men mainly believed the war was to emancipate the slaves. Confederates\nfought to protect southern society, and slavery as an integral part of it.[45]\nAddressing the causes, Eric_Foner would relate a historical context with\nmultidimensional political, social and economic variables. The several causes\nunited in the moment by a consolidating nationalism. A social movement that was\nindividualist, egalitarian and perfectionist grew to a political democratic\nmajority attacking slavery, and slavery\'s defense in the Southern pre&#8211;\nindustrial traditional society brought the two sides to war.[46]\n\n<i> States\' rights \n</i>\n\nMain article: States\'_rights\n[Men_lined_up_along_a_tree_line_are_shot_by_men_on_horseback.]\nMarais_des_Cygnes_massacre of anti&#8211;slavery Kansans. May 19, 1858.\nAt the time, most Americans agreed that states had certain rights, however,\nthey did not agree as to whether or not those rights carried over when a\ncitizen left the boundaries of the state. The Southern position was that\ncitizens of every state had the right to take their property anywhere in the\nU.S. and not have it taken away; specifically they could bring their slaves\nanywhere and they would remain slaves. Northerners rejected this \"right\"\nbecause it would violate the right of a free state to outlaw slavery within its\nborders. Republicans committed to ending the expansion of slavery were among\nthose opposed to any such right to bring slaves and slavery into the free\nstates and territories. The Dred_Scott Supreme Court decision of 1857 bolstered\nthe Southern case within territories, and angered the North.[47]\nSecondly, the South argued that each state had the right to secede_leave the\nUnion_at any time, that the Constitution was a \"compact\" or agreement among\nthe states. Northerners (including President Buchanan) rejected that notion as\nopposed to the will of the Founding Fathers who said they were setting up a\n\"perpetual union\".[47] Historian James McPherson writes concerning states\'\nrights and other non&#8211;slavery explanations:\n     While one or more of these interpretations remain popular among the\n     Sons_of_Confederate_Veterans and other Southern heritage groups, few\n     professional historians now subscribe to them. Of all these\n     interpretations, the states\'&#8211;rights argument is perhaps the weakest.\n     It fails to ask the question, states\' rights for what purpose?\n     States\' rights, or sovereignty, was always more a means than an end,\n     an instrument to achieve a certain goal more than a principle.[48]\n\n<i> Sectionalism and cotton trade \n</i>\n\n[Map_of_U.S._showing_two_kinds_of_Union_states,_two_phases_of_secession_and\nterritories.]\nStatus of the states, 1861.\n   States that seceded before April 15, 1861\n   States that seceded after April 15, 1861\n   Union states that permitted slavery\n   Union states that banned slavery\n   Territories\nSectionalism refers to the different economies, social structure, customs and\npolitical values of the North and South.[49][50] It increased steadily between\n1800 and 1860 as the North, which phased slavery out of existence,\nindustrialized, urbanized and built prosperous farms, while the deep South\nconcentrated on plantation agriculture based on slave labor, together with\nsubsistence farming for the poor whites. The South expanded into rich new lands\nin the Southwest (from Alabama to Texas).[51] The primary export for the South\nwas cotton; a crop that had expanded growth, demand, and was essential for the\nindustrial revolution in Europe and the USA. Most came from the South. By 1860\nthe cotton trade held 57 percent of the value of all American exports worth\n$191,000,000 turning the South into a cotton empire. [52]\nThe use of slaves declined in the border states and could barely survive in\ncities and industrial areas (it was fading out in cities such as Baltimore,\nLouisville, and St. Louis), so a South based on slavery was rural and non&#8211;\nindustrial. On the other hand, as the demand for cotton grew, the price of\nslaves who picked it soared. Historians have debated whether economic\ndifferences between the industrial Northeast and the agricultural South helped\ncause the war. Most historians now disagree with the economic_determinism of\nhistorian Charles_A._Beard in the 1920s and emphasize that Northern and\nSouthern economies were largely complementary. While socially different, the\nsections economically benefited each other.[53][54]\nConfederates counted on King_Cotton for economic leverage on Europe.\nFears of slave revolts and abolitionist propaganda made the South militantly\nhostile to abolitionism.[55][56] Southerners complained that it was the North\nthat was changing, and was prone to new \"isms\", while the South remained true\nto historic republican_values of the Founding Fathers (many of whom owned\nslaves, including Washington, Jefferson, and Madison). Lincoln said that\nRepublicans were following the tradition of the framers of the Constitution\n(including the Northwest_Ordinance and the Missouri_Compromise) by preventing\nexpansion of slavery.[57]\nIn the 1840s and 50s, the issue of accepting slavery (in the guise of rejecting\nslave&#8211;owning bishops and missionaries) split the nation\'s largest religious\ndenominations (the Methodist, Baptist and Presbyterian churches) into separate\nNorthern and Southern denominations.[58] Industrialization meant that seven\nEuropean immigrants out of eight settled in the North. The movement of twice as\nmany whites leaving the South for the North as vice versa contributed to the\nSouth\'s defensive&#8211;aggressive political behavior.[59]\n\n<i> Protectionism \n</i>\n\nMain articles: King_Cotton, Protectionism_in_the_United_States and Infant\nindustry\nNew_Orleans the largest cotton exporting port for New England and Great Britain\ntextile mills, shipping Mississippi River Valley goods from North, South and\nBorder states.\nHistorically, southern slave&#8211;holding states, because of their low cost manual\nlabor, had little perceived need for mechanization, and supported having the\nright to sell_cotton and purchase manufactured goods from any nation. Northern\nstates, which had heavily invested in their still&#8211;nascent manufacturing, could\nnot compete with the full&#8211;fledged industries of Europe in offering high prices\nfor cotton imported from the South and low prices for manufactured exports in\nreturn. Thus, northern manufacturing interests supported tariffs and\nprotectionism while southern planters demanded free trade.[60]\nThe Democrats in Congress, controlled by Southerners, wrote the tariff laws in\nthe 1830s, 1840s, and 1850s, and kept reducing rates so that the 1857 rates\nwere the lowest since 1816. The South had no complaints but the low rates\nangered Northern industrialists and factory workers, especially in\nPennsylvania, who demanded protection for their growing iron industry. The\nWhigs and Republicans complained because they favored high tariffs to stimulate\nindustrial growth, and Republicans called for an increase in tariffs in the\n1860 election. The increases were finally enacted in 1861 after Southerners\nresigned their seats in Congress.[61][62]\nHistorians in the 1920s emphasized the tariff issue but since the 1950s they\nhave minimized it, noting that few Southerners in 1860_61 said it was of\ncentral importance to them. Some secessionist documents do mention the tariff\nissue, though not nearly as often as the preservation of slavery.[citation\nneeded]\n\n<i> Slave power and free soil \n</i>\n\nMain article: Slave_Power\n\"A Ride for Liberty\" (1862). An unassisted family of fugitive slaves charges\nfor the safety of Union lines.\nAntislavery forces in the North identified the \"Slave Power\" as a direct threat\nto republican_values. They argued that rich slave owners were using political\npower to take control of the Presidency, Congress and the Supreme Court, thus\nthreatening the rights of the citizens of the North.[N_5][63]\n\"Free soil\" was a Northern demand that the new lands opening up in the west be\navailable to independent yeoman farmers and not be bought out by rich slave\nowners who would buy up the best land and work it with slaves, forcing the\nwhite farmers onto marginal lands. This was the basis of the Free_Soil_Party of\n1848, and a main theme of the Republican Party.[64] Free Soilers and\nRepublicans demanded a homestead_law that would give government land to\nsettlers; it was defeated by Southerners who feared it would attract to the\nwest European immigrants and poor Southern whites.[65]\n\n<i> Territorial crisis \n</i>\n\nFurther information: Slave_and_free_states\nBetween 1803 and 1854, the United States achieved a vast expansion of territory\nthrough purchase, negotiation, and conquest. Of the states carved out of these\nterritories by 1845, all had entered the union as slave states: Louisiana,\nMissouri, Arkansas, Florida and Texas, as well as the southern portions of\nAlabama and Mississippi. These were balanced by new free states created within\nthe U.S.\' original boundary east of the Mississippi_River, and the free state\nof Iowa in 1846. With the conquest of northern Mexico, including California in\n1848, slaveholding interests looked forward to the institution flourishing in\nmuch of these lands as well. Southerners also anticipated garnering slaves and\nslave states in Cuba and Central America.[66][67] Northern free soil interests\nvigorously sought to curtail any further expansion of slave soil. It was these\nterritorial disputes that the proslavery and antislavery forces collided over.\n[68] The Compromise_of_1850 over California, tried again to reach some\npolitical settlement on these issues.\nThe existence of slavery in the southern states was far less politically\npolarizing than the explosive question of the territorial expansion of the\ninstitution westward.[69] Moreover, Americans were informed by two well&#8211;\nestablished readings of the Constitution regarding human bondage: first, that\nthe slave states had complete autonomy over the institution within their\nboundaries, and second, that the domestic slave trade _ trade among the\nstates _ was immune to federal interference.[70][71] The only feasible\nstrategy available to attack slavery was to restrict its expansion into the new\nterritories.[72] Slaveholding interests fully grasped the danger that this\nstrategy posed to them.[73] Both the South and the North drew the same\nconclusion: \"The power to decide the question of slavery for the territories\nwas the power to determine the future of slavery itself.\"[74][75]\nSen. Stephen Douglas, author of the Kansas&#8211;Nebraska_Act of 1854\nSen. John J. Crittenden, author of the Crittenden_Compromise bill of 1860\nBy 1860, four doctrines had emerged to answer the question of federal control\nin the territories, and they all claimed they were sanctioned by the\nConstitution, implicitly or explicitly. Two of the \"conservative\" doctrines\nemphasized the written text and historical precedents of the founding document\n(specifically, the Northwest_Ordinance and the Missouri_Compromise), while the\nother two doctrines developed arguments that transcended the Constitution.[76]\nThe first of these \"conservative\" theories, represented by the Constitutional\nUnion_Party, argued that the historical designation of free and slave\napportionments in territories (as done in the Missouri Compromise) should\nbecome a Constitutional mandate. The Crittenden_Compromise of 1860 was an\nexpression of this view.[77]\nThe second doctrine of Congressional preeminence, championed by Abraham_Lincoln\nand the Republican_Party, insisted that the Constitution did not bind\nlegislators to a policy of balance _ that slavery could be excluded\naltogether (as done in the Northwest Ordinance) in a territory at the\ndiscretion of Congress[78] _ with one caveat: the due_process_clause_of_the\nFifth_Amendment must apply. In other words, Congress could restrict human\nbondage, but never establish it. The Wilmot_Proviso announced this position in\n1846.[79]\nOf the two doctrines that rejected federal authority, one was articulated by\nnorthern Democrat of Illinois Senator Stephen_A._Douglas, and the other by\nsouthern Democratic Senator Jefferson_Davis of Mississippi and Vice&#8211;President\nJohn_C._Breckinridge of Kentucky.[80]\nDouglas proclaimed the doctrine of territorial or \"popular\" sovereignty &#8211; which\ndeclared that the settlers in a territory had the same rights as states in the\nUnion to establish or disestablish slavery _ a purely local matter. Congress,\nhaving created the territory, was barred, according to Douglas, from exercising\nany authority in domestic matters. To do so would violate historic traditions\nof self&#8211;government, implicit in the US Constitution.[81] The Kansas&#8211;Nebraska\nAct of 1854 legislated this doctrine.[82] In Kansas Territory, years of pro_and\nanti&#8211;slavery_violence and political conflict erupted; the congressional House\nof Representatives voted to admit Kansas as a free state in early 1860, but its\nadmission in the Senate was delayed until after the 1860 elections, when\nsouthern senators began to leave.[83]\nThe fourth in this quartet is the theory of state sovereignty (\"states\'\nrights\"),[84] also known as the \"Calhoun doctrine\",[85] named after the South\nCarolinian political theorist and statesman John_C._Calhoun.[86] Rejecting the\narguments for federal authority or self&#8211;government, state sovereignty would\nempower states to promote the expansion of slavery as part of the Federal Union\nunder the US Constitution _ and not merely as an argument for secession. The\nbasic premise was that all authority regarding matters of slavery in the\nterritories resided in each state. The role of the federal government was\nmerely to enable the implementation of state laws when residents of the states\nentered the territories.[87] The Calhoun doctrine asserted that the federal\ngovernment in the territories was only the agent of the several sovereign\nstates, and hence incapable of forbidding the bringing into any territory of\nanything that was legal property in any state. State sovereignty, in other\nwords, gave the laws of the slaveholding states extra&#8211;jurisdictional effect.\n[88]\n     States\' rights\" was an ideology formulated and applied as a means of\n     advancing slave state interests through federal authority.[89] As\n     historian Thomas L. Krannawitter points out, the \"Southern demand for\n     federal slave protection represented a demand for an unprecedented\n     expansion of federal power.\"[90][91]\nBy 1860, these four doctrines comprised the major ideologies presented to the\nAmerican public on the matters of slavery, the territories and the US\nConstitution.[92]\n\n<i> National elections \n</i>\n\nBeginning in the American Revolution and accelerating after the War of 1812,\nthe people of the United States grew in their sense of country as an important\nexample to the world of a national republic of political liberty and personal\nrights. Previous regional independence movements such as the Greek revolt in\nthe Ottoman Empire, division and redivision in the Latin American political\nmap, and the British&#8211;French Crimean triumph leading to an interest in redrawing\nEurope along cultural differences, all conspired to make for a time of upheaval\nand uncertainty about the basis of the nation&#8211;state. In the world of 19th\ncentury self&#8211;made Americans, growing in prosperity, population and expanding\nwestward, \"freedom\" could mean personal liberty or property rights. The\nunresolved difference would cause failure_first in their political\ninstitutions, then in their civil life together.\n\n<i> Nationalism and honor \n</i>\n\n[Middle&#8211;aged_man_in_a_beard_posed_sitting_in_a_suit,_vest_and_bowtie.]\nAbraham Lincoln\n16th U.S. President (1861_1865)\nNationalism was a powerful force in the early 19th century, with famous\nspokesmen such as Andrew_Jackson and Daniel_Webster. While practically all\nNortherners supported the Union, Southerners were split between those loyal to\nthe entire United States (called \"unionists\") and those loyal primarily to the\nsouthern region and then the Confederacy.[93] C._Vann_Woodward said of the\nlatter group,\n     \"A great slave society &#8230; had grown up and miraculously flourished\n     in the heart of a thoroughly bourgeois and partly puritanical\n     republic. It had renounced its bourgeois origins and elaborated and\n     painfully rationalized its institutional, legal, metaphysical, and\n     religious defenses &#8230; When the crisis came it chose to fight. It\n     proved to be the death struggle of a society, which went down in\n     ruins.[94]\nPerceived insults to Southern collective honor included the enormous popularity\nof Uncle_Tom\'s_Cabin (1852)[95] and the_actions_of_abolitionist_John_Brown_in\ntrying_to_incite_a_slave_rebellion in 1859.[96]\nWhile the South moved toward a Southern nationalism, leaders in the North were\nalso becoming more nationally minded, and rejected any notion of splitting the\nUnion. The Republican national electoral platform of 1860 warned that\nRepublicans regarded disunion as treason and would not tolerate it: \"We\ndenounce those threats of disunion &#8230; as denying the vital principles of a\nfree government, and as an avowal of contemplated treason, which it is the\nimperative duty of an indignant people sternly to rebuke and forever silence.\"\n[97] The South ignored the warnings: Southerners did not realize how ardently\nthe North would fight to hold the Union together.[98]\n\n<i> Lincoln\'s election \n</i>\n\nMain article: United_States_presidential_election,_1860\nThe election of Lincoln in November 1860 was the final trigger for secession.\n[99] Efforts at compromise, including the \"Corwin_Amendment\" and the\n\"Crittenden_Compromise\", failed. Southern leaders feared that Lincoln would\nstop the expansion of slavery and put it on a course toward extinction. The\nslave states, which had already become a minority in the House of\nRepresentatives, were now facing a future as a perpetual minority in the Senate\nand Electoral College against an increasingly powerful North. Before Lincoln\ntook office in March 1861, seven slave states had declared their secession and\njoined to form the Confederacy.\n\n<u> Secession and war begins \n</u>\n\nThe first published imprint of secession\n\n<i> Resolves and developments \n</i>\n\n\n<i> Secession of South Carolina \n</i>\n\nSee also: Antebellum_South_Carolina\nPrior to the war, South_Carolina did more than any other Southern state to\nadvance the notion that a state had the right to nullify federal laws and,\neven, secede from the United States. South Carolina adopted the \"Declaration_of\nthe_Immediate_Causes_Which_Induce_and_Justify_the_Secession_of_South_Carolina\nfrom_the_Federal_Union\" on December 24, 1860. It argued for states\' rights for\nslave owners in the South, but contained a complaint about states\' rights in\nthe North in the form of opposition to the Fugitive_Slave_Act, claiming that\nNorthern states were not fulfilling their federal obligations under the\nConstitution.\n\n<i> Secession winter \n</i>\n\nBefore Lincoln took office, seven states had declared their secession from the\nUnion. They did not actually declare independence, because in their opinion\nthey were already sovereign states and were merely withdrawing from a compact\nmade with other sovereign states. They established a new federal government,\nthe Confederate_States_of_America on February 4, 1861.[100] They took control\nof federal forts and other properties within their boundaries with little\nresistance from outgoing President James_Buchanan, whose term ended on March 4,\n1861. Buchanan said that the Dred_Scott_decision was proof that the South had\nno reason for secession, and that the Union \"&#8230; was intended to be perpetual,\"\nbut that, \"The power by force of arms to compel a State to remain in the\nUnion,\" was not among the \"&#8230; enumerated powers granted to Congress.\"[101] One\nquarter of the U.S. Army &#8211; the entire garrison in Texas &#8211; was surrendered in\nFebruary 1861 to state forces by its commanding general, David_E._Twiggs, who\nthen joined the Confederacy.\nAs Southerners resigned their seats in the Senate and the House, Republicans\nwere able to pass bills for projects that had been blocked by Southern Senators\nbefore the war, including the Morrill_Tariff, land grant colleges (the Morill\nAct), a Homestead_Act, a transcontinental railroad (the Pacific_Railway_Acts),\n[102] the National_Banking_Act and the authorization of United_States_Notes by\nthe Legal Tender Act of 1862. The Revenue_Act_of_1861 introduced the income_tax\nto help finance the war.\n\n<i> States align \n</i>\n\n\n<i> Confederate states \n</i>\n\nMain article: Confederate_States_of_America\n[Middle&#8211;aged_man_in_a_goatee_posed_standing_in_a_suit,_vest_and_bowtie]\nJefferson_Davis, President of Confederacy (1861_1865)\nSeven Deep_South cotton states seceded by February 1861, starting with South\nCarolina, Mississippi, Florida, Alabama, Georgia, Louisiana, and Texas. These\nseven states formed the Confederate States of America (February 4, 1861), with\nJefferson_Davis as president, and a governmental_structure closely modeled on\nthe U.S._Constitution.[103]\nFollowing the attack_on_Fort_Sumter, President Lincoln called for a volunteer\narmy from each state. Within two months, an additional four Southern slave\nstates declared their secession and joined the Confederacy: Virginia, Arkansas,\nNorth_Carolina and Tennessee. The northwestern portion of Virginia subsequently\nseceded from Virginia, joining the Union as the new state of West_Virginia on\nJune 20, 1863. By the end of 1861, Missouri and Kentucky were effectively under\nUnion control, with Confederate state governments in exile.\nAmong the ordinances of secession passed by the individual states, those of\nthree _ Texas, Alabama, and Virginia _ specifically mentioned the plight of\nthe \'slaveholding states\' at the hands of northern abolitionists. The rest make\nno mention of the slavery issue, and are often brief announcements of the\ndissolution of ties by the legislatures.[104] However, at least four states _\nSouth Carolina,[105] Mississippi,[106] Georgia,[107] and Texas[108] _ also\npassed lengthy and detailed explanations of their causes for secession, all of\nwhich laid the blame squarely on the movement to abolish slavery and that\nmovement\'s influence over the politics of the northern states, The southern\nstates believed slaveholding was a constitutional right because of the Fugitive\nslave_clause of the Constitution. In a message to the Confederate Congress on\nApril 29, 1861 Jefferson_Davis cited both the tariff and slavery for the\nSouth\'s secession.[109]\n\n<i> Union states \n</i>\n\nMain article: Union_(American_Civil_War)\nTwenty&#8211;three states remained loyal to the Union: California, Connecticut,\nDelaware, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Maine, Maryland,\nMassachusetts, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, New_Hampshire, New_Jersey, New\nYork, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Rhode_Island, Vermont, and Wisconsin. During\nthe war, Nevada and West_Virginia joined as new states of the Union. Tennessee\nand Louisiana were returned to Union military control early in the war.\nThe territories of Colorado, Dakota, Nebraska, Nevada, New_Mexico, Utah, and\nWashington fought on the Union side. Several slave&#8211;holding_Native_American\ntribes supported the Confederacy, giving the Indian_Territory (now Oklahoma) a\nsmall, bloody civil war.[110][111][112]\n\n<i> Border states \n</i>\n\nMain article: Border_states_(American_Civil_War)\nThe border states in the Union were West_Virginia (which separated from\nVirginia and became a new state), and four of the five northernmost slave\nstates (Maryland, Delaware, Missouri, and Kentucky).\nMaryland had numerous anti&#8211;Lincoln officials who tolerated anti&#8211;army rioting_in\nBaltimore and the burning of bridges, both aimed at hindering the passage of\ntroops to the South. (Maryland\'s legislature voted to stay in the Union, but\nalso rejected hostilities with the South, voting to close Maryland\'s rail lines\nto prevent them from being used for war.[7]) Lincoln responded by establishing\nmartial_law, and unilaterally suspending habeas_corpus, in Maryland, along with\nsending in militia units from the North.[113] Lincoln rapidly took control of\nMaryland and the District of Columbia, by seizing many prominent figures,\nincluding arresting &#8531; of the members of the Maryland_General_Assembly on the\nday it reconvened.[7][114] All were held without trial, ignoring a ruling by\nthe Chief Justice of the U.S. Supreme Court Roger_Taney, a Maryland native,\nthat only Congress (and not the president) could suspend habeas corpus, (Ex\nparte_Merryman). Indeed, federal troops imprisoned a prominent Baltimore\nnewspaper editor, Frank_Key_Howard, Francis Scott Key\'s grandson, after he\ncriticized Lincoln in an editorial for ignoring the Supreme Court Chief\nJustice\'s ruling.[115]\n[Map_of_U.S._showing_three_new_states,_with_two_kinds_of_Confederate\nterritorial_control.]\nThe Union: blue, yellow (slave);\nThe Confederacy: brown\n*territories in light shades; control of Confederate&#8211;occupied territories\ndisputed\nIn Missouri, an elected_convention on secession voted decisively to remain\nwithin the Union. When pro&#8211;Confederate Governor Claiborne_F._Jackson called out\nthe state militia, it was attacked by federal forces under General Nathaniel\nLyon, who chased the governor and the rest of the State Guard to the\nsouthwestern corner of the state. (See also: Missouri_secession). In the\nresulting vacuum, the convention on secession reconvened and took power as the\nUnionist provisional government of Missouri.[116]\nKentucky did not secede; for a time, it declared itself neutral. When\nConfederate forces entered the state in September 1861, neutrality ended and\nthe state reaffirmed its Union status, while trying to maintain slavery. During\na brief invasion by Confederate forces, Confederate sympathizers organized a\nsecession convention, inaugurated a governor, and gained recognition from the\nConfederacy. The rebel government soon went into exile and never controlled\nKentucky.[117]\nAfter Virginia\'s secession, a Unionist government in Wheeling asked 48 counties\nto vote on an ordinance to create a new state on October 24, 1861. A voter\nturnout of 34 percent approved the statehood bill (96 percent approving).[118] The inclusion\nof 24 secessionist counties[119] in the state and the ensuing guerrilla war\nengaged about 40,000 Federal troops for much of the war.[120][121] Congress\nadmitted West_Virginia to the Union on June 20, 1863. West Virginia provided\nabout 20,000_22,000 soldiers to both the Confederacy and the Union.[122]\nA Unionist secession attempt occurred in East_Tennessee, but was suppressed by\nthe Confederacy, which arrested over 3,000 men suspected of being loyal to the\nUnion. They were held without trial.[123]\n\n<i> Beginning the war \n</i>\n\nFor more details on this topic, see Battle_of_Fort_Sumter.\nLincoln\'s victory in the presidential_election_of_1860 triggered South\nCarolina\'s declaration of secession from the Union in December, and six more\nstates did so by February 1861. A pre&#8211;war February Peace_Conference_of_1861 met\nin Washington, Lincoln sneaking into town to stay in the Conference\'s hotel its\nlast three days. The attempt failed at resolving the crisis, but the remaining\neight slave states rejected pleas to join the Confederacy following a two&#8211;to&#8211;\none no&#8211;vote in Virginia\'s First Secessionist Convention on April 4, 1861.[124]\n\n<i> Lincoln\'s policy \n</i>\n\nSince December, secessionists with and without state forces had seized Federal\nCourt Houses, U.S. Treasury mints and post offices. Southern governors ordered\nmilitia mobilization, seized most of the federal forts and cannons within their\nboundaries and U.S. armories of infantry weapons. The governors in big&#8211;state\nRepublican strongholds of Massachusetts, New York, and Pennsylvania quietly\nbegan buying weapons and training militia units themselves.[125] President\nBuchanan protested seizure of Federal property, but made no military response\napart from a failed attempt on January 9, 1861 to resupply Fort Sumter using\nthe ship Star_of_the_West, which was fired upon by South Carolina forces and\nturned back before it reached the fort.[124]\n[Merchant_steamer,_Ft._Sumter_center_horizon,_Confederate_battery_smoke_left\nand_right.]\nMerchant Star_of_the_West intended to resupply Ft. Sumter. Lincoln\'s policy to\nhold federal property was unlike Buchanan\'s\nOn March 4, 1861, Abraham Lincoln was sworn in as President. In his inaugural\naddress, he argued that the Constitution was a more_perfect_union than the\nearlier Articles_of_Confederation_and_Perpetual_Union, that it was a binding\ncontract, and called any secession \"legally void\".[126] He had no intent to\ninvade Southern states, nor did he intend to end slavery where it existed, but\nsaid that he would use force to maintain possession of federal property. The\ngovernment would make no move to recover post offices, and if resisted, mail\ndelivery would end at state lines. Where popular conditions did not allow\npeaceful enforcement of Federal law, U.S. Marshals and Judges would be\nwithdrawn. No mention was made of bullion lost from U.S. mints in Louisiana,\nGeorgia and North Carolina. In Lincoln\'s inaugural address, U.S. policy would\nonly collect import duties at its ports; there could be no serious injury to\njustify revolution in the politics of four years. His speech closed with a plea\nfor restoration of the bonds of union.[127]\nThe South sent delegations to Washington and offered to pay for the federal\nproperties and enter into a peace treaty with the United States. Lincoln\nrejected any negotiations with Confederate agents because he claimed the\nConfederacy was not a legitimate government, and that making any treaty with it\nwould be tantamount to recognition of it as a sovereign government.[128]\nSecretary of State William_Seward who at that time saw himself as the real\ngovernor or \"prime minister\" behind the throne of the inexperienced Lincoln,\nengaged in unauthorized and indirect negotiations that failed.[128] President\nLincoln was determined to hold all remaining Union&#8211;occupied forts in the\nConfederacy, Fort_Monroe in Virginia, in Florida, Fort_Pickens, Fort_Jefferson,\nand Fort_Taylor, and in the cockpit of secession, Charleston, South Carolina\'s\nFort_Sumter.\n\n<i> Battle of Fort Sumter \n</i>\n\nMain article: Battle_of_Fort_Sumter\n[Crowd_surrounding_an_equestrian_statue_toped_by_a_huge_U.S._flag.]\nMass meeting April 20, 1861 to support the Government at Washington\'s\nequestrian statue in Union_Square NYC\nFt. Sumter was located in the middle of the harbor of Charleston, South\nCarolina, where the U.S. fort\'s garrison had withdrawn to avoid incidents with\nlocal militias in the streets of the city. Unlike Buchanan who allowed\ncommanders to relinquish possession to avoid bloodshed, Lincoln required Maj.\nAnderson to hold on until fired upon. Jefferson Davis ordered the surrender of\nthe fort. Anderson gave a conditional reply that the Confederate government\nrejected, and Davis ordered P._G._T._Beauregard to attack the fort before a\nrelief expedition could arrive. Troops under Beauregard bombarded Fort Sumter\non April 12_13, forcing its capitulation.\nThe attack on Fort Sumter rallied the North to the defense of American\nnationalism. Historian Allan Nevins says:\n      The thunderclap of Sumter produced a startling crystallization of\n      Northern sentiment&#8230;. Anger swept the land. From every side came news of\n      mass meetings, speeches, resolutions, tenders of business support, the\n      muster of companies and regiments, the determined action of governors and\n      legislatures.\"[129][130]\nLincoln called on all the states to send forces to recapture the fort and other\nfederal properties. He cited presidential powers given by the Militia_Acts_of\n1792. With the scale of the rebellion apparently small so far, Lincoln called\nfor only 75,000_volunteers for 90 days.[131] The governor of Massachusetts had\nstate regiments on trains headed south the next day. In western Missouri, local\nsecessionists seized Liberty_Arsenal.[132] On May 3, 1861, Lincoln called for\nan additional 42,000 volunteers for a period of three years.[133]\nFour states in the middle and upper South had repeatedly rejected Confederate\novertures, but now Virginia, Tennessee, Arkansas, and North_Carolina refused to\nsend forces against their neighbors, declared their secession, and joined the\nConfederacy. To reward Virginia, the Confederate capital was moved to Richmond.\n[134]\n\n<u> War \n</u>\n\nSee also: List_of_American_Civil_War_battles and Military_leadership_in_the\nAmerican_Civil_War\nThe Civil War was a contest marked by the ferocity and frequency of battle.\nOver four years, 237 named battles were fought, as were many more minor actions\nand skirmishes, which were often characterized by their bitter intensity and\nhigh casualties. \"The American Civil War was to prove one of the most ferocious\nwars ever fought\". Without geographic objectives, the only target for each side\nwas the enemy\'s soldier.[135]\n\n<i> Mobilization \n</i>\n\nAs the first seven states began organizing a Confederacy in Montgomery, the\nentire US army numbered 16,000. However, Northern governors had begun to\nmobilize their militias.[136] The Confederate Congress authorized the new\nnation up to 100,000 troops sent by governors as early as February. By May,\nJefferson Davis was pushing for 100,000 men under arms for one year or the\nduration, and that was answered in kind by the U.S. Congress.[137]\nIn the first year of the war, both sides had far more volunteers than they\ncould effectively train and equip. After the initial enthusiasm faded, reliance\non the cohort of young men who came of age every year and wanted to join was\nnot enough. Both sides used a draft law_conscription_as a device to\nencourage or force volunteering; relatively few were actually drafted and\nserved. The Confederacy passed a draft law in April 1862 for young men aged 18\nto 35; overseers of slaves, government officials, and clergymen were exempt.\n[138] The U.S. Congress followed in July, authorizing a militia draft within a\nstate when it could not meet its quota with volunteers. European immigrants\njoined the Union_Army in large numbers, including 177,000 born in Germany and\n144,000 born in Ireland.[139]\nUnion soldiers before Marye\'s Heights, Second_Fredericksburg\nConfederate dead overrun at Marye\'s Heights, reoccupied next day May 4, 1863.\nWhen the Emancipation Proclamation went into effect in January 1863, ex&#8211;slaves\nwere energetically recruited by the states, and used to meet the state quotas.\nStates and local communities offered higher and higher cash bonuses for white\nvolunteers. Congress tightened the law in March 1863. Men selected in the draft\ncould provide substitutes or, until mid&#8211;1864, pay commutation money. Many\neligibles pooled their money to cover the cost of anyone drafted. Families used\nthe substitute provision to select which man should go into the army and which\nshould stay home. There was much evasion and overt resistance to the draft,\nespecially in Catholic areas. The great draft_riot_in_New_York_City_in_July\n1863 involved Irish immigrants who had been signed up as citizens to swell the\nvote of the city\'s_Democratic_political_machine, not realizing it made them\nliable for the draft.[140] Of the 168,649 men procured for the Union through\nthe draft, 117,986 were substitutes, leaving only 50,663 who had their personal\nservices conscripted.[141]\nNorth and South, the draft laws were highly unpopular. In the North, some\n120,000 men evaded conscription, many of them fleeing to Canada, and another\n280,000 soldiers deserted during the war.[142] At least 100,000 Southerners\ndeserted, or about 10 percent. In the South, many men deserted temporarily to take\ncare of their distressed families, then returned to their units.[143] In the\nNorth, \"bounty jumpers\" enlisted to get the generous bonus, deserted, then went\nback to a second recruiting station under a different name to sign up again for\na second bonus; 141 were caught and executed.[144]\nRioters attacking a building during the New_York_anti&#8211;draft_riots of 1863\nFrom a tiny frontier force in 1860, the Union and Confederate armies had grown\ninto the \"largest and most efficient armies in the world\" within a few years.\nEuropean observers at the time dismissed them as amateur and unprofessional,\nbut British historian John_Keegan\'s assessment is that each outmatched the\nFrench, Prussian and Russian armies of the time, and but for the Atlantic,\nwould have threatened any of them with defeat.[145]\n\n<i> Motivation \n</i>\n\nPerman and Taylor (2010) say that historians are of two minds on why millions\nof men seemed so eager to fight, suffer and die over four years:\n     Some historians emphasize that Civil War soldiers were driven by\n     political ideology, holding firm beliefs about the importance of\n     liberty, Union, or state rights, or about the need to protect or to\n     destroy slavery. Others point to less overtly political reasons to\n     fight, such as the defense of one\'s home and family, or the honor and\n     brotherhood to be preserved when fighting alongside other men. Most\n     historians agree that no matter what a soldier thought about when he\n     went into the war, the experience of combat affected him profoundly\n     and sometimes altered his reasons for continuing the fight.\"[146]\n\n<i> Prisoners \n</i>\n\nMain article: American_Civil_War_prison_camps\nAt the start of the civil war, a system of paroles operated. Captives agreed\nnot to fight until they were officially exchanged. Meanwhile they were held in\ncamps run by their own army where they were paid but not allowed to perform any\nmilitary duties.[147] The system of exchanges collapsed in 1863 when the\nConfederacy refused to exchange black prisoners. After that, about 56,000 of\nthe 409,000 POWs died in prisons during the war, accounting for nearly 10 percent of\nthe conflict\'s fatalities.[148]\n\n<i> Naval war \n</i>\n\nThe small U.S._Navy of 1861 was rapidly enlarged to 6,000 officers and 45,000\nmen in 1865, with 671 vessels, having a tonnage of 510,396.[149][150] Its\nmission was to blockade Confederate ports, take control of the river system,\ndefend against Confederate raiders on the high seas, and be ready for a\npossible war with the British Royal_Navy.[151] Meanwhile, the main riverine war\nwas fought in the West, where a series of major rivers gave access to the\nConfederate heartland, if the U.S. Navy could take control. In the East, the\nNavy supplied and moved army forces about, and occasionally shelled Confederate\ninstallations.\n\n<i> Union blockade \n</i>\n\nMain article: Union_blockade\n[A_cartoon_map_of_the_South_surrounded_by_a_snake.]\nGeneral Scott\'s \"Anaconda_Plan\" 1861. Tightening naval blockade, rebels out of\nMissouri along Mississippi River, Kentucky Unionists sit on the fence, idled\ncotton industry illustrated in Georgia\nBy early 1861, General Winfield_Scott had devised the Anaconda_Plan to win the\nwar with as little bloodshed as possible.[152] Scott argued that a Union\nblockade of the main ports would weaken the Confederate economy. Lincoln\nadopted parts of the plan, but he overruled Scott\'s caution about 90&#8211;day\nvolunteers. Public opinion, however, demanded an immediate attack by the army\nto capture Richmond.[153]\nIn April 1861, Lincoln announced the Union blockade of all Southern ports;\ncommercial ships could not get insurance and regular traffic ended. The South\nblundered in embargoing cotton exports in 1861 before the blockade was\neffective; by the time they realized the mistake, it was too late. \"King\nCotton\" was dead, as the South could export less than 10 percent of its cotton. The\nblockade shut down the ten Confederate seaports with railheads that moved\nalmost all the cotton, especially New Orleans, Mobile, and Charleston. By June\n1861, warships were stationed off the principal Southern ports, and a year\nlater nearly 300 ships were in service.[154]\n\n<i> Modern navy evolves \n</i>\n\nThe Civil War prompted the industrial revolution and subsequently many naval\ninnovations emerged during this time, most notably the advent of the ironclad\nwarship. It began when the Confederacy, knowing they had to meet or match the\nUnion\'s naval superiority, responded to the Union blockade by building or\nconverting more than 130 vessels, including twenty&#8211;six ironclads and floating\nbatteries.[155] Only half of these saw active service. Many were equipped with\nram bows, creating \"ram fever\" among Union squadrons wherever they threatened.\nBut in the face of overwhelming Union superiority and the Union\'s own ironclad\nwarships, they were unsuccessful.[156]\nThe Confederacy experimented with a submarine, which did not work well,[157]\nand with building an ironclad ship, the CSS_Virginia, which was based on\nrebuilding a sunken Union ship, the Merrimack. On its first foray on March 8,\n1862, the Virginia decimated the Union\'s wooden fleet, but the next day the\nfirst Union ironclad, the USS_Monitor, arrived to challenge it. The Battle_of\nthe_Ironclads was a draw, but it marks the worldwide transition to ironclad\nwarships.[158]\nThe Confederacy lost the Virginia when the ship was scuttled to prevent\ncapture, and the Union built many copies of the Monitor. Lacking the technology\nto build effective warships, the Confederacy attempted to obtain warships from\nBritain.[159]\n\n<i> Blockade runners \n</i>\n\nMain article: Blockade_runners_of_the_American_Civil_War\nBritish investors built small, fast, steam&#8211;driven blockade_runners that traded\narms and luxuries brought in from Britain through Bermuda, Cuba, and the\nBahamas in return for high&#8211;priced cotton. The ships were so small that only a\nsmall amount of cotton went out. When the Union Navy seized a blockade runner,\nthe ship and cargo were condemned as a Prize_of_war and sold, with the proceeds\ngiven to the Navy sailors; the captured crewmen were mostly British and they\nwere simply released.[160] The Southern economy nearly collapsed during the\nwar. There were multiple reasons for this: the severe deterioration of food\nsupplies, especially in cities, the failure of Southern railroads, the loss of\ncontrol of the main rivers, foraging by Northern armies, and the seizure of\nanimals and crops by Confederate armies. Historians agree that the blockade was\na major factor in ruining the Confederate economy. However, Wise argues that\nthey provided just enough of a lifeline to allow Lee to continue fighting for\nadditional months, thanks to fresh supplies of 400,000 rifles, lead, blankets,\nand boots that the homefront economy could no longer supply.[161]\nGunline of nine Union ironclads. South_Atlantic_Blockading_Squadron off\nCharleston. Continuous blockade of all major ports was sustained by North\'s\noverwhelming war production\n\n<i> Economic impact \n</i>\n\nSurdam argues that the blockade was a powerful weapon that eventually ruined\nthe Southern economy, at the cost of few lives in combat. Practically, the\nentire Confederate cotton crop was useless (although it was sold to Union\ntraders), costing the Confederacy its main source of income. Critical imports\nwere scarce and the coastal trade was largely ended as well.[162] The measure\nof the blockade\'s success was not the few ships that slipped through, but the\nthousands that never tried it. Merchant ships owned in Europe could not get\ninsurance and were too slow to evade the blockade; they simply stopped calling\nat Confederate ports.[163]\nTo fight an offensive war, the Confederacy purchased ships from Britain,\nconverted them to warships, and raided American merchant ships in the Atlantic\nand Pacific oceans. Insurance rates skyrocketed and the American flag virtually\ndisappeared from international waters. However, the same ships were reflagged\nwith European flags and continued unmolested.[156] After the war, the U.S.\ndemanded that Britain pay for the damage done, and Britain paid the U.S. $15\nmillion in 1871.[164]\n\n<i> Rivers \n</i>\n\nThe 1862 Union strategy called for simultaneous advances along four axes.\nMcClellan would lead the main thrust in Virginia towards Richmond. Ohio forces\nwere to advance through Kentucky into Tennessee, the Missouri Department would\ndrive south along the Mississippi River, and the westernmost attack would\noriginate from Kansas.[165]\nClashes on the rivers were melees of ironclads, cottonclads gunboats and rams,\ncomplicated by torpedoes and fire rafts\nUlysses_Grant used river transport and Andrew_Foote\'s gunboats of the Western\nFlotilla to threaten the Confederacy\'s \"Gibraltar of the West\" at Columbus,\nKentucky. Grant was rebuffed at Belmont, but cut off Columbus. The\nConfederates, lacking their own gunboats, were forced to retreat and the Union\ntook control of western Kentucky in March 1862.[166]\nIn addition to ocean&#8211;going warships coming up the Mississippi, the Union Navy\nused timberclads, tinclads, and armored gunboats. Shipyards at Cairo, Illinois,\nand St. Louis built new boats or modified steamboats for action.[167] They took\ncontrol of the Red, Tennessee, Cumberland, Mississippi, and Ohio rivers after\nvictories at Fort_Henry and Fort_Donelson, and supplied Grant\'s forces as he\nmoved into Tennessee. At Shiloh, (Pittsburg Landing) in Tennessee in April\n1862, the Confederates made a surprise attack that pushed Union forces against\nthe river as night fell. Overnight, the Navy landed additional reinforcements,\nand Grant counter&#8211;attacked. Grant and the Union won a decisive victory _ the\nfirst battle with the high casualty rates that would repeat over and over.[168]\nMemphis fell to Union forces and became a key base for further advances south\nalong the Mississippi River. In April 1862, US Naval forces under Farragut ran\npast Confederate defenses south of New Orleans. Confederates abandoned the\ncity, which gave the Union a critical anchor in the deep South.[169]\nNaval forces assisted Grant in his long, complex campaign that resulted in the\nsurrender of Vicksburg in July 1863, and full Union control of the Mississippi\nsoon after.[170]\n\n<i> Eastern theater \n</i>\n\nFor more details on this topic, see Eastern_Theater_of_the_American_Civil_War.\nBecause of the fierce resistance of a few initial Confederate forces at\nManassas, Virginia, in July 1861, a march by Union troops under the command of\nMaj._Gen. Irvin_McDowell on the Confederate forces there was halted in the\nFirst_Battle_of_Bull_Run, or First Manassas.[171] McDowell\'s troops were forced\nback to Washington, D.C., by the Confederates under the command of Generals\nJoseph_E._Johnston and P._G._T._Beauregard. It was in this battle that\nConfederate General Thomas_Jackson received the nickname of \"Stonewall\" because\nhe stood like a stone wall against Union troops.[172]\nThe Battle_of_Antietam, the Civil War\'s deadliest one&#8211;day fight. Union troops\ncommitted piecemeal had little effect\nConfederate ironclads at Norfolk and New Orleans dispersed blockade, until\nUnion ironclads could defeat them\nAlarmed at the loss, and in an attempt to prevent more slave states from\nleaving the Union, the U.S._Congress passed the Crittenden&#8211;Johnson_Resolution\non July 25 of that year, which stated that the war was being fought to preserve\nthe Union and not to end slavery.\nMaj. Gen. George_B._McClellan took command of the Union Army_of_the_Potomac on\nJuly 26 (he was briefly general&#8211;in&#8211;chief of all the Union armies, but was\nsubsequently relieved of that post in favor of Maj. Gen. Henry_W._Halleck), and\nthe war began in earnest in 1862. Upon the strong urging of President Lincoln\nto begin offensive operations, McClellan attacked Virginia in the spring of\n1862 by way of the peninsula between the York_River and James_River, southeast\nof Richmond. Although McClellan\'s army reached the gates of Richmond in the\nPeninsula_Campaign,[173][174][175] Johnston halted his advance at the Battle_of\nSeven_Pines, then General Robert_E._Lee and top subordinates James_Longstreet\nand Stonewall Jackson defeated McClellan in the Seven_Days_Battles and forced\nhis retreat.[176] The Northern_Virginia_Campaign, which included the Second\nBattle_of_Bull_Run, ended in yet another victory for the South.[177] McClellan\nresisted General&#8211;in&#8211;Chief Halleck\'s orders to send reinforcements to John\nPope\'s Union Army_of_Virginia, which made it easier for Lee\'s Confederates to\ndefeat twice the number of combined enemy troops.\nEmboldened by Second Bull Run, the Confederacy made its first invasion of the\nNorth. General Lee led 45,000 men of the Army_of_Northern_Virginia across the\nPotomac_River into Maryland on September 5. Lincoln then restored Pope\'s troops\nto McClellan. McClellan and Lee fought at the Battle_of_Antietam near\nSharpsburg, Maryland, on September 17, 1862, the bloodiest single day in United\nStates military history.[176][178] Lee\'s army, checked at last, returned to\nVirginia before McClellan could destroy it. Antietam is considered a Union\nvictory because it halted Lee\'s invasion of the North and provided an\nopportunity for Lincoln to announce his Emancipation_Proclamation.[179]\nUnion forces performing a bayonet charge, 1862\nWhen the cautious McClellan failed to follow up on Antietam, he was replaced by\nMaj. Gen. Ambrose_Burnside. Burnside was soon defeated at the Battle_of\nFredericksburg[180] on December 13, 1862, when more than 12,000 Union soldiers\nwere killed or wounded during repeated futile frontal assaults against Marye\'s\nHeights. After the battle, Burnside was replaced by Maj. Gen. Joseph_Hooker.\nHooker, too, proved unable to defeat Lee\'s army; despite outnumbering the\nConfederates by more than two to one, he was humiliated in the Battle_of\nChancellorsville in May 1863.[181] Gen. Stonewall Jackson was mortally wounded\nby_his_own_men during the battle and subsequently died of complications. Gen.\nHooker was replaced by Maj. Gen. George_Meade during Lee\'s second invasion of\nthe North, in June. Meade defeated Lee at the Battle_of_Gettysburg (July 1 to\n3, 1863).[182] This was the bloodiest battle of the war, and has been called\nthe war\'s turning_point. Pickett\'s_Charge on July 3 is often considered the\nhigh&#8211;water_mark_of_the_Confederacy because it signaled the collapse of serious\nConfederate threats of victory. Lee\'s army suffered 28,000 casualties (versus\nMeade\'s 23,000).[183] However, Lincoln was angry that Meade failed to intercept\nLee\'s retreat, and after Meade\'s inconclusive fall campaign, Lincoln turned to\nthe Western Theater for new leadership. At the same time, the Confederate\nstronghold of Vicksburg surrendered, giving the Union control of the\nMississippi River, permanently isolating the western Confederacy, and producing\nthe new leader Lincoln needed, Ulysses_S._Grant.\n\n<i> Western theater \n</i>\n\nFor more details on this topic, see Western_Theater_of_the_American_Civil_War.\nWhile the Confederate forces had numerous successes in the Eastern Theater,\nthey were defeated many times in the West. They were driven from Missouri early\nin the war as a result of the Battle_of_Pea_Ridge.[184] Leonidas_Polk\'s\ninvasion of Columbus, Kentucky ended Kentucky\'s policy of neutrality and turned\nthat state against the Confederacy. Nashville and central Tennessee fell to the\nUnion early in 1862, leading to attrition of local food supplies and livestock\nand a breakdown in social organization.\nThe Battle_of_Chickamauga, the highest two&#8211;day losses. Confederate victory held\noff Union offensive for two months.\nNew_Orleans_captured. Union ironclads forced passage, sank Confederate fleet,\ndestroyed batteries, held docks for Army.\nThe Mississippi was opened to Union traffic to the southern border of Tennessee\nwith the taking of Island_No._10 and New_Madrid, Missouri, and then Memphis,\nTennessee. In April 1862, the Union_Navy captured New Orleans,[185] which\nallowed Union forces to begin moving up the Mississippi. Only the fortress city\nof Vicksburg, Mississippi, prevented Union control of the entire river.\nGeneral Braxton_Bragg\'s second Confederate invasion of Kentucky ended with a\nmeaningless victory over Maj. Gen. Don_Carlos_Buell at the Battle_of\nPerryville, although Bragg was forced to end his attempt at invading Kentucky\nand retreat due to lack of support for the Confederacy in that state.[186]\nBragg was narrowly defeated by Maj. Gen. William_Rosecrans at the Battle_of\nStones_River in Tennessee.[187]\nThe one clear Confederate victory in the West was the Battle_of_Chickamauga.\nBragg, reinforced by Lt. Gen. James_Longstreet\'s corps (from Lee\'s army in the\neast), defeated Rosecrans, despite the heroic defensive stand of Maj. Gen.\nGeorge_Henry_Thomas. Rosecrans retreated to Chattanooga, which Bragg then\nbesieged.\nThe Union\'s key strategist and tactician in the West was Ulysses_S._Grant, who\nwon victories at Forts Henry and Donelson (by which the Union seized control of\nthe Tennessee and Cumberland Rivers); the_Battle_of_Shiloh;[188] and the Battle\nof_Vicksburg,[189] which cemented Union control of the Mississippi River and is\nconsidered one of the turning_points of the war. Grant marched to the relief of\nRosecrans and defeated Bragg at the Third_Battle_of_Chattanooga,[190] driving\nConfederate forces out of Tennessee and opening a route to Atlanta and the\nheart of the Confederacy.\n\n<i> Trans&#8211;Mississippi \n</i>\n\nFor more details on Missouri in the Civil War, see Trans&#8211;Mississippi_Theater_of\nthe_American_Civil_War.\nQuantrill\'s_Raid captured a hotel in free&#8211;state Kansas for a day in a town of\n2,000, burned 185 buildings, killed 182 men and boys[191]\nNathaniel_Lyon secured St. Louis docks and arsenal, led Union forces to expel\nMissouri Confederate forces and government[192]\nExtensive guerrilla_warfare characterized the trans&#8211;Mississippi region, as the\nConfederacy lacked the troops and the logistics to support regular armies that\ncould challenge Union control.[193] Roving Confederate bands such as\nQuantrill\'s_Raiders terrorized the countryside, striking both military\ninstallations and civilian settlements.[194] The \"Sons of Liberty\" and \"Order\nof the American Knights\" attacked pro&#8211;Union people, elected officeholders, and\nunarmed uniformed soldiers. These partisans could not be entirely driven out of\nthe state of Missouri until an entire regular Union infantry division was\nengaged.\nBy 1864, these violent activities harmed the nationwide anti&#8211;war movement\norganizing against the re&#8211;election of Lincoln. Missouri not only stayed in the\nUnion, Lincoln took 70 percent of the vote for re&#8211;election.[191]\nNumerous small&#8211;scale military actions south and west of Missouri sought to\ncontrol Indian_Territory and New_Mexico_Territory for the Union. The Union\nrepulsed Confederate incursions into New Mexico in 1862, and the exiled Arizona\ngovernment withdrew into Texas. In the Indian Territory, civil war broke out\nwithin tribes. About 12,000 Indian warriors fought for the Confederacy, and\nsmaller numbers for the Union.[195] The most prominent Cherokee was Brigadier\nGeneral Stand_Watie, the last Confederate general to surrender.[196]\nAfter the fall of Vicksburg in July 1863, General Kirby_Smith in Texas was\ninformed by Jefferson Davis that he could expect no further help from east of\nthe Mississippi River. Although he lacked resources to beat Union armies, he\nbuilt up a formidable arsenal at Tyler, along with his own Kirby Smithdom\neconomy, a virtual \"independent fiefdom\" in Texas, including railroad\nconstruction and international smuggling. The Union in turn did not directly\nengage him.[197] Its 1864 Red_River_Campaign to take Shreveport, Louisiana was\na failure and Texas remained in Confederate hands throughout the war.\n\n<i> End of war \n</i>\n\n\n<i> Conquest of Virginia \n</i>\n\nAt the beginning of 1864, Lincoln made Grant commander of all Union armies.\nGrant made his headquarters with the Army of the Potomac, and put Maj. Gen.\nWilliam_Tecumseh_Sherman in command of most of the western armies. Grant\nunderstood the concept of total_war and believed, along with Lincoln and\nSherman, that only the utter defeat of Confederate forces and their economic\nbase would end the war.[198] This was total war not in killing civilians but\nrather in taking provisions and forage and destroying homes, farms, and\nrailroads, that Grant said \"would otherwise have gone to the support of\nsecession and rebellion. This policy I believe exercised a material influence\nin hastening the end._[199] Grant devised a coordinated strategy that would\nstrike at the entire Confederacy from multiple directions. Generals George\nMeade and Benjamin_Butler were ordered to move against Lee near Richmond,\nGeneral Franz_Sigel (and later Philip_Sheridan) were to attack_the_Shenandoah\nValley, General Sherman was to capture Atlanta and march to the sea (the\nAtlantic Ocean), Generals George_Crook and William_W._Averell were to operate\nagainst railroad supply lines in West_Virginia, and Maj. Gen. Nathaniel_P.\nBanks was to capture Mobile, Alabama.\nThese dead are from Ewell\'s May 1864 attack at Spotsylvania, delaying Grant\'s\nadvance on Richmond in the Wilderness\nThe_Peacemakers on the River_Queen, March 1865. Sherman, Grant, Lincoln, and\nPorter pictured discussing plans for the last weeks of the Civil War\nGrant\'s army set out on the Overland_Campaign with the goal of drawing Lee into\na defense of Richmond, where they would attempt to pin down and destroy the\nConfederate army. The Union army first attempted to maneuver past Lee and\nfought several battles, notably at the Wilderness, Spotsylvania, and Cold\nHarbor. These battles resulted in heavy losses on both sides, and forced Lee\'s\nConfederates to fall back repeatedly.[200] An attempt to outflank Lee from the\nsouth failed under Butler, who was trapped inside the Bermuda_Hundred river\nbend. Each battle resulted in setbacks for the Union that mirrored what they\nhad suffered under prior generals, though unlike those prior generals, Grant\nfought on rather than retreat. Grant was tenacious and kept pressing Lee\'s Army\nof Northern Virginia back to Richmond.[201] While Lee was preparing for an\nattack on Richmond, Grant unexpectedly turned south to cross the James_River\nand began the protracted Siege_of_Petersburg, where the two armies engaged in\ntrench_warfare for over nine months.\nGrant finally found a commander, General Philip_Sheridan, aggressive enough to\nprevail in the Valley_Campaigns_of_1864. Sheridan was initially repelled at the\nBattle_of_New_Market by former U.S. Vice President and Confederate Gen. John_C.\nBreckinridge. The Battle of New Market was the Confederacy\'s last major victory\nof the war. After redoubling his efforts, Sheridan defeated Maj. Gen. Jubal_A.\nEarly in a series of battles, including a final decisive defeat at the Battle\nof_Cedar_Creek. Sheridan then proceeded to destroy the agricultural base of the\nShenandoah_Valley, a strategy similar to the tactics Sherman later employed in\nGeorgia.[202]\nMeanwhile, Sherman maneuvered from Chattanooga to Atlanta, defeating\nConfederate Generals Joseph_E._Johnston and John_Bell_Hood along the way. The\nfall_of_Atlanta on September 2, 1864, guaranteed the reelection of Lincoln as\npresident.[203] Hood left the Atlanta area to swing around and menace Sherman\'s\nsupply lines and invade Tennessee in the Franklin&#8211;Nashville_Campaign.[204]\nUnion Maj. Gen. John_Schofield defeated Hood at the Battle_of_Franklin, and\nGeorge_H._Thomas dealt Hood a massive defeat at the Battle_of_Nashville,\neffectively destroying Hood\'s army.\nLeaving Atlanta, and his base of supplies, Sherman\'s army marched with an\nunknown destination, laying waste to about 20 percent of the farms in Georgia in his\n\"March_to_the_Sea\". He reached the Atlantic Ocean at Savannah, Georgia in\nDecember 1864. Sherman\'s army was followed by thousands of freed slaves; there\nwere no major battles along the March. Sherman turned north through South\nCarolina and North Carolina to approach the Confederate Virginia lines from the\nsouth, increasing the pressure on Lee\'s army.[205]\nLee\'s army, thinned by desertion and casualties, was now much smaller than\nGrant\'s. One last Confederate attempt to break the Union hold on Petersburg\nfailed at the decisive Battle_of_Five_Forks (sometimes called \"the Waterloo of\nthe Confederacy\") on April 1. This meant that the Union now controlled the\nentire perimeter surrounding Richmond&#8211;Petersburg, completely cutting it off\nfrom the Confederacy. Realizing that the capital was now lost, Lee decided to\nevacuate his army. The Confederate capital fell to the Union_XXV_Corps,\ncomposed of black troops. The remaining Confederate units fled west and after a\ndefeat at Sayler\'s_Creek.[206]\n\n<i> Confederacy surrenders \n</i>\n\n[A_map_of_the_U.S._South_showing_shrinking_territory_under_rebel_control.]\nMap of Confederate territory losses year by year\nMain article: Conclusion_of_the_American_Civil_War\nInitially, Lee was not intending to surrender, but rather to regroup at the\nvillage_of_Appomattox_Court_House, where supplies were to be waiting, and to\ncontinue the war. Grant chased Lee, and got in front of him, so that when Lee\'s\narmy reached Appomattox Court House, they were surrounded. After an initial\nbattle, Lee decided that the fight was now hopeless, and so he surrendered his\nArmy of Northern Virginia on April 9, 1865, at the McLean_House.[207] In an\nuntraditional gesture and as a sign of Grant\'s respect and anticipation of\npeacefully restoring Confederate states to the Union, Lee was permitted to keep\nhis sword and his horse, Traveller. On April 14, 1865, President Lincoln was\nshot by John_Wilkes_Booth, a Southern sympathizer. Lincoln died early the next\nmorning, and Andrew_Johnson became the president. Meanwhile, Confederate forces\nacross the South surrendered as news of Lee\'s surrender reached them.[208]\nPresident Johnson officially declared a virtual end to the insurrection on May\n9, 1865; Confederate President Jefferson_Davis was captured the following day.\n[1] On June 23, 1865, Cherokee leader Stand_Watie was the last Confederate\nGeneral to surrender his forces.[209]\n\n<u> Diplomacy \n</u>\n\nMain articles: Britain_in_the_American_Civil_War and France_in_the_American\nCivil_War\nEurope in the 1860s was more fragmented than it had been since before the\nAmerican Revolution. France was in a weakened state while Britain was still\nshocked by its own poor performance in the Crimean_War.[210] France was unable\nor unwilling to support either side without Britain, where popular support\nremained with the Union though elite opinion was more varied. They were further\ndistracted by Germany and Italy, who were experiencing unification troubles,\nand by Russia, who was almost unflinching in its support for the Union.[210]\n[211]\nThough the Confederacy hoped that Britain and France would join them against\nthe Union, this was never likely, and so they instead tried to bring Britain\nand France in as mediators.[210][211] The Union, under Lincoln and Secretary of\nState William_H._Seward worked to block this, and threatened war if any country\nofficially recognized the existence of the Confederate States of America. In\n1861, Southerners voluntarily embargoed cotton shipments, hoping to start an\neconomic depression in Europe that would force Britain to enter the war to get\ncotton, but this did not work.[212] Worse, Europe developed other cotton\nsuppliers, which they found superior, hindering the South\'s recovery after the\nwar.\n[A_group_of_twenty&#8211;six_sailors_posing_around_a_rifled_naval_cannon.]\nCrewmembers of USS_Wissahickon by the ship\'s 11&#8211;inch (280 mm) Dahlgren_gun,\ncirca 1863\nCotton_diplomacy proved a failure as Europe had a surplus of cotton, while the\n1860_62 crop failures in Europe made the North\'s grain exports of critical\nimportance. It also helped to turn European opinion further away from the\nConfederacy. It was said that \"King Corn was more powerful than King Cotton\",\nas U.S. grain went from a quarter of the British import trade to almost half.\n[212] When Britain did face a cotton shortage, it was temporary, being replaced\nby increased cultivation in Egypt and India. Meanwhile, the war created\nemployment for arms makers, ironworkers, and British ships to transport\nweapons.[213]\nCharles_Francis_Adams proved particularly adept as minister to Britain for the\nU.S. and Britain was reluctant to boldly challenge the blockade. The\nConfederacy purchased several warships from commercial shipbuilders in Britain\n(CSS_Alabama, CSS_Shenandoah, CSS_Tennessee, CSS_Tallahassee, CSS_Florida, and\nsome others). The most famous, the CSS_Alabama, did considerable damage and led\nto serious postwar_disputes. However, public opinion against slavery created a\npolitical liability for European politicians, especially in Britain (which had\nabolished slavery in her colonies in 1834).[214]\nWar loomed in late 1861 between the U.S. and Britain over the Trent_affair,\ninvolving the U.S. Navy\'s boarding of the British_mail_steamer Trent to seize\ntwo Confederate diplomats. However, London and Washington were able to smooth\nover the problem after Lincoln released the two. In 1862, the British\nconsidered mediation &#8211; though even such an offer would have risked war with the\nU.S. British Prime Minister Lord_Palmerston reportedly read Uncle_Tom\'s_Cabin\nthree times when deciding on this.[214]\nThe Union victory in the Battle_of_Antietam caused them to delay this decision.\nThe Emancipation_Proclamation over time would reinforce the political liability\nof supporting the Confederacy. Despite sympathy for the Confederacy, France\'s\nown seizure_of_Mexico ultimately deterred them from war with the Union.\nConfederate offers late in the war to end slavery in return for diplomatic\nrecognition were not seriously considered by London or Paris. After 1863, the\nPolish_revolt_against_Russia further distracted the European powers, and\nensured that they would remain neutral.[215]\n\n<u> Victory and aftermath \n</u>\n\n\n<i> Results \n</i>\n\nThe causes_of_the_war, the reasons for its outcome, and even the_name_of_the\nwar_itself are subjects of lingering contention today. The North and West grew\nrich while the once&#8211;rich South became poor for a century. The national\npolitical power of the slaveowners and rich southerners ended. Historians are\nless sure about the results of the postwar Reconstruction, especially regarding\nthe second class citizenship of the Freedmen and their poverty.\nHistorians have debated whether the Confederacy could have won the war. Most\nscholars, such as James_McPherson, argue that Confederate victory was at least\npossible.[216] McPherson argues that the North\'s advantage in population and\nresources made Northern victory likely but not guaranteed. He also argues that\nif the Confederacy had fought using unconventional tactics, they would have\nmore easily been able to hold out long enough to exhaust the Union.[217]\n           Comparison of Union and CSA, 1860_1864[218]\n                Year      Union                 CSA\nPopulation      1860      22,100,000 (71 percent)      9,100,000 (29 percent)\n                1864      28,800,000 (90 percent)[N_6] 3,000,000 (10 percent)[219]\nFree            1860      21,700,000 (81 percent)      5,600,000 (19 percent)\nSlave           1860      400,000 (11 percent)         3,500,000 (89 percent)\n                1864      negligible            1,900,000[N_7]\nSoldiers        1860_2,100,000 (67 percent)       1,064,000 (33 percent)\nRailroad miles  1860      21,800 (71 percent)          8,800 (29 percent)\n                1864      29,100 (98 percent)[220]     negligible\nManufactures    1860      90 percent                   10 percent\n                1864      98 percent                   negligible\nArms production 1860      97 percent                   3 percent\n                1864      98 percent                   negligible\nCotton bales    1860      negligible            4,500,000\n                1864      300,000               negligible\nExports         1860      30 percent                   70 percent\n                1864      98 percent                   negligible\nConfederates did not need to invade and hold enemy territory to win, but only\nneeded to fight a defensive war to convince the North that the cost of winning\nwas too high. The North needed to conquer and hold vast stretches of enemy\nterritory and defeat Confederate armies to win.[217] Lincoln was not a military\ndictator, and could only continue to fight the war as long as the American\npublic supported a continuation of the war. The Confederacy sought to win\nindependence by out&#8211;lasting Lincoln; however, after Atlanta fell and Lincoln\ndefeated McClellan in the election of 1864, all hope for a political victory\nfor the South ended. At that point, Lincoln had secured the support of the\nRepublicans, War Democrats, the border states, emancipated slaves, and the\nneutrality of Britain and France. By defeating the Democrats and McClellan, he\nalso defeated the Copperheads and their peace platform.[221]\nMany scholars argue that the Union held an insurmountable long&#8211;term advantage\nover the Confederacy in industrial strength and population. Confederate\nactions, they argue, only delayed defeat.[222][223] Civil War historian Shelby\nFoote expressed this view succinctly: \"I think that the North fought that war\nwith one hand behind its back &#8230; If there had been more Southern victories,\nand a lot more, the North simply would have brought that other hand out from\nbehind its back. I don\'t think the South ever had a chance to win that War.\"\n[224]\nA minority view among historians is that the Confederacy lost because, as E.\nMerton_Coulter put it,\"people did not will hard enough and long enough to win.\"\n[225][226] Marxist historian Armstead Robinson agrees, pointing to a class\nconflict in the Confederates army between the slave owners and the larger\nnumber of non&#8211;owners. He argues that the non&#8211;owner soldiers grew embittered\nabout fighting to preserve slavery, and fought less enthusiastically. He\nattributes the major Confederate defeats in 1863 at Vicksburg and Missionary\nRidge to this class conflict.[227] However, most historians reject the\nargument.[228] James_M._McPherson, after reading thousands of letters written\nby Confederate soldiers, found strong patriotism that continued to the end;\nthey truly believed they were fighting for freedom and liberty. Even as the\nConfederacy was visibly collapsing in 1864&#8211;5, he says most Confederate soldiers\nwere fighting hard.[229] Historian Gary Gallagher cites General Sherman who in\nearly 1864 commented, \"The devils seem to have a determination that cannot but\nbe admired.\" Despite their loss of slaves and wealth, with starvation looming,\nSherman continued, \"yet I see no sign of let up _ some few deserters _\nplenty tired of war, but the masses determined to fight it out.\"[230]\nAlso important were Lincoln\'s eloquence in rationalizing the national purpose\nand his skill in keeping the border states committed to the Union cause.\nAlthough Lincoln\'s approach to emancipation was slow, the Emancipation\nProclamation was an effective use of the President\'s war powers.[231] The\nConfederate government failed in its attempt to get Europe involved in the war\nmilitarily, particularly Britain and France. Southern leaders needed to get\nEuropean powers to help break up the blockade the Union had created around the\nSouthern ports and cities.\nLincoln\'s naval blockade was 95 percent effective at stopping trade goods; as a\nresult, imports and exports to the South declined significantly. The abundance\nof European cotton and Britain\'s hostility to the institution of slavery, along\nwith Lincoln\'s Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico naval blockades, severely decreased\nany chance that either Britain or France would enter the war.\nHistorian Don Doyle has argued that the Union victory had a major impact on the\ncourse of world history.[232] The Union victory energized popular democratic\nforces. A Confederate victory, on the other hand, would have meant a new birth\nof slavery, not freedom. Historian Fergus Bordewich, following Doyle, argues\nthat:\n      The North\'s victory decisively proved the durability of democratic\n      government. Confederate independence, on the other hand, would have\n      established An American model for reactionary politics and race&#8211;based\n      repression that would likely have cast an international shadow into the\n      twentieth century and perhaps beyond.\"[233]\n\n<i> Costs \n</i>\n\nThe war produced about 1,030,000 casualties (3 percent of the population), including\nabout 620,000 soldier deaths_two&#8211;thirds by disease, and 50,000 civilians.\n[234] Binghamton University historian J. David Hacker believes the number of\nsoldier deaths was approximately 750,000, 20 percent higher than traditionally\nestimated, and possibly as high as 850,000.[235][236] The war accounted for\nroughly as many American deaths as all American deaths in other U.S. wars\ncombined.[237]\nOne in thirteen veterans were amputees\nRemains of both sides were reinterred\nNational cemetery in Andersonville,_GA\nBased on 1860 census figures, 8 percent of all white males aged 13 to 43 died in the\nwar, including 6 percent in the North and 18 percent in the South.[238][239] About 56,000\nsoldiers died_in_prison_camps during the War.[240] An estimated 60,000 men lost\nlimbs in the war.[241]\nUnion army dead, amounting to 15 percent of the over two million who served, was\nbroken down as follows:[2]\n    * 110,070 killed in action (67,000) or died of wounds (43,000).\n    * 199,790 died of disease (75 percent of which was due to the war, the remainder\n      would have occurred in civilian life anyway)\n    * 24,866 died in Confederate prison camps\n    * 9,058 killed by accidents or drowning\n    * 15,741 other/unknown deaths\n    * 359,528 total dead\nIn addition there were 4,523 deaths in the Navy (2,112 in battle) and 460 in\nthe Marines (148 in battle).[3]\nBlack troops made up 10 percent of the Union death toll, they amounted to 15 percent of\ndisease deaths but less than 3 percent of those killed in battle.[2] Losses among\nAfrican_Americans were high, in the last year and a half and from all reported\ncasualties, approximately 20 percent of all African Americans enrolled in the military\nlost their lives during the Civil War.[242]:16 Notably, their mortality rate\nwas significantly higher than white soldiers;\n    [We] \"find, according to the revised official data, that of the\n    slightly over two millions troops in the United States Volunteers, over\n    316,000 died (from all causes), or 15.2 percent. Of the 67,000 Regular Army\n    (white) troops, 8.6 percent, or not quite 6,000, died. Of the approximately\nâ180,000 United_States_Colored_Troops, however, over 36,000 died, or     _\n    20.5 percent. In other words, the mortality \"rate\" amongst the United States\n    Colored Troops in the Civil War was thirty&#8211;five percent greater than\n    that among other troops, notwithstanding the fact that the former were\n    not enrolled until some eighteen months after the fighting began\".\n    Herbert_Aptheker[242]:16\nIncomplete Confederate records list 74,524 killed and died of wounds and 59,292\ndied of disease. Including Confederate estimates of battle losses where no\nrecords exist would bring the Confederate death toll to 94,000 killed and died\nof wounds.[2]\nUnion soldier on his release from Andersonville, 1865\nLosses can be viewed as high considering that the defeat_of_Mexico in 1846_48\nresulted in fewer than 2,000 soldiers killed in battle. One reason for the high\nnumber of battle deaths during the war was the use of Napoleonic tactics, such\nas charging. With the advent of more accurate rifled barrels, MiniÃ©_balls and\n(near the end of the war for the Union_army) repeating firearms such as the\nSpencer_Repeating_Rifle and the Henry_Repeating_Rifle, soldiers were mowed down\nwhen standing in lines in the open. This led to the adoption of trench_warfare,\na style of fighting that defined the better part of World War I.\nThe wealth amassed in slaves and slavery for the Confederacy\'s 3.5 million\nblacks effectively ended when Union armies arrived; they were nearly all freed\nby the Emancipation Proclamation. Slaves in the border states and those located\nin some former Confederate territory occupied before the Emancipation\nProclamation were freed by state action or (on December 6, 1865) by the\nThirteenth_Amendment.\nThe war destroyed much of the wealth that had existed in the South. All\naccumulated investment Confederate bonds was forfeit; most banks and railroads\nwere bankrupt. Income per person in the South dropped to less than 40 percent of that\nof the North, a condition that lasted until well into the 20th century.\nSouthern influence in the US federal government, previously considerable, was\ngreatly diminished until the latter half of the 20th century.[243] The full\nrestoration of the Union was the work of a highly contentious postwar era known\nas Reconstruction.\n\n<i> Emancipation \n</i>\n\n\n<i> Issue of Slavery During the War \n</i>\n\nWhile not all Southerners saw themselves as fighting to preserve slavery, most\nof the officers and over a third of the rank and file in Lee\'s army had close\nfamily ties to slavery. To Northerners, in contrast, the motivation was\nprimarily to preserve the Union, not to abolish slavery.[244] Abraham Lincoln\nconsistently made preserving the Union the central goal of the war, though he\nincreasingly saw slavery as a crucial issue and made ending it an additional\ngoal.[245] Lincoln\'s decision to issue the Emancipation_Proclamation angered\nboth Peace_Democrats (\"Copperheads\") and War_Democrats, but energized most\nRepublicans.[246] By warning that free blacks would flood the North, Democrats\nmade gains in the 1862_elections, but they did not gain control of Congress.\nThe Republicans\' counterargument that slavery was the mainstay of the enemy\nsteadily gained support, with the Democrats losing decisively in the 1863\nelections in the northern state of Ohio when they tried to resurrect anti&#8211;black\nsentiment.[247]\n\n<i> Emancipation Proclamation \n</i>\n\nMain article: Emancipation_Proclamation\nThe Emancipation Proclamation enabled African&#8211;Americans, both free blacks and\nescaped slaves, to join the Union Army.[N_8] About 190,000 volunteered, further\nenhancing the numerical advantage the Union armies enjoyed over the\nConfederates, who did not dare emulate the equivalent manpower source for fear\nof fundamentally undermining the legitimacy of slavery.[N_9]\nDuring the Civil War, sentiment concerning slaves, enslavement and emancipation\nin the United States was divided. In 1861, Lincoln worried that premature\nattempts at emancipation would mean the loss of the border states, and that \"to\nlose Kentucky is nearly the same as to lose the whole game.\"[253] Copperheads\nand some War_Democrats opposed emancipation, although the latter eventually\naccepted it as part of total_war needed to save the Union.[254]\nContrabands _ fugitive slaves _ cooks, laundresses, laborers, teamsters,\nrailroad repair crews _ fled to the Union Army, but were not officially freed\nuntil 1863 Emancipation_Proclamation\nIn 1863, the Union army accepted Freedmen. Here are Black and White teen&#8211;aged\nsoldiers.\nAt first, Lincoln reversed attempts at emancipation by Secretary of War Simon\nCameron and Generals John_C._FrÃ©mont (in Missouri) and David_Hunter (in South\nCarolina, Georgia and Florida) to keep the loyalty of the border states and the\nWar Democrats. Lincoln warned the border states that a more radical type of\nemancipation would happen if his gradual plan based on compensated emancipation\nand voluntary colonization was rejected.[255] But only the District of Columbia\naccepted Lincoln\'s gradual plan, which was enacted by Congress. When Lincoln\ntold his cabinet about his proposed emancipation proclamation, Seward advised\nLincoln to wait for a victory before issuing it, as to do otherwise would seem\nlike \"our last shriek on the retreat\".[256] Lincoln laid the groundwork for\npublic support in an open letter published letter to abolitionist Horace\nGreeley\'s newspaper.[257]\nIn September 1862, the Battle_of_Antietam provided this opportunity, and the\nsubsequent War_Governors\'_Conference added support for the proclamation.[258]\nLincoln issued his preliminary Emancipation_Proclamation on September 22, 1862,\nand his final Emancipation Proclamation on January 1, 1863. In his letter to\nAlbert_G._Hodges, Lincoln explained his belief that \"If slavery is not wrong,\nnothing is wrong &#8230; And yet I have never understood that the Presidency\nconferred upon me an unrestricted right to act officially upon this judgment\nand feeling &#8230; I claim not to have controlled events, but confess plainly that\nevents have controlled me.\"[259]\nLincoln\'s moderate approach succeeded in inducing border states, War Democrats\nand emancipated slaves to fight for the Union. The Union&#8211;controlled border\nstates (Kentucky, Missouri, Maryland, Delaware and West Virginia) and Union&#8211;\ncontrolled regions around New Orleans, Norfolk and elsewhere, were not covered\nby the Emancipation Proclamation. All abolished slavery on their own, except\nKentucky and Delaware.[260]\nSince the Emancipation Proclamation was based on the President\'s war powers, it\nonly included territory held by Confederates at the time. However, the\nProclamation became a symbol of the Union\'s growing commitment to add\nemancipation to the Union\'s definition of liberty.[261] The Emancipation\nProclamation greatly reduced the Confederacy\'s hope of getting aid from Britain\nor France.[262] By late 1864, Lincoln was playing a leading role in getting\nCongress to vote for the Thirteenth_Amendment, which made emancipation\nuniversal and permanent.[263]\n\n<i> Texas v. White \n</i>\n\nIn Texas_v._White, 74 U.S. 700 (1869) the United States Supreme Court ruled\nthat Texas had remained a state ever since it first joined the Union, despite\nclaims that it joined the Confederate_States_of_America; the court further held\nthat the Constitution did not permit states to unilaterally secede from the\nUnited States, and that the ordinances of secession, and all the acts of the\nlegislatures within seceding states intended to give effect to such ordinances,\nwere \"absolutely null\", under the constitution.[264]\n\n<i> Reconstruction \n</i>\n\nMain article: Reconstruction_Era_of_the_United_States\nNorthern teachers traveled into the South to provide education and training for\nthe newly freed population.\nReconstruction began during the war, with the Emancipation Proclamation of\nJanuary 1, 1863 and continued to 1877.[265] It comprised multiple complex\nmethods to resolve the war, the most important of which were the three\n\"Reconstruction_Amendments\" to the Constitution, which remain in effect to the\npresent time: the 13th (1865), the 14th (1868) and the 15th (1870). From the\nUnion perspective, the goals of Reconstruction were to guarantee the Union\nvictory on the battlefield by reuniting the Union; to guarantee a \"republican\nform_of_government for the ex&#8211;Confederate states; and to permanently end\nslavery_and prevent semi&#8211;slavery status.[266]\nPresident Johnson took a lenient approach and saw the achievement of the main\nwar goals as realized in 1865, when each ex&#8211;rebel state repudiated secession\nand ratified the Thirteenth Amendment. Radical_Republicans demanded strong\nproof that Confederate nationalism was dead and the slaves were truly free.\nThey came to the fore after the 1866 elections and undid much of Johnson\'s\nwork. They used the Army to dissolve Southern state governments and hold new\nelections with Freedmen voting. The result was a Republican coalition that took\npower in ten states for varying lengths of time, staying in power with the help\nof U.S. Army units and black voters. Grant was elected president in 1868 and\ncontinued the Radical policies. Meanwhile the Freedmen\'s_Bureau, started by\nLincoln in 1865 to help the freed slaves, played a major role in helping the\nblacks and arranging work for them. In opposition, paramilitary groups such as\nthe first Ku_Klux_Klan used violence to thwart these efforts.[267]\nThe \"Liberal_Republicans\" argued the war goals had been achieved and\nReconstruction should end. They ran a ticket in 1872 but were decisively\ndefeated as Grant was reelected. In 1874, Democrats took control of Congress\nand opposed any more reconstruction. The disputed 1876 elections were resolved\nby the Compromise_of_1877, which put Republican Rutherford_B._Hayes in the\nWhite House. He pulled out the last federal troops and the last Republican\nstate governments in the South collapsed, marking the end of Civil War and\nReconstruction.[268]\n\n<u> Memory and historiography \n</u>\n\nMonument to the Grand_Army_of_the_Republic, a Union veteran organization\nCherokee_Confederates reunion in New Orleans, 1903\nThe Civil War is one of the central events in America\'s collective memory.\nThere are innumerable statues, commemorations, books and archival collections.\nThe memory includes the home front, military affairs, the treatment of\nsoldiers, both living and dead, in the war\'s aftermath, depictions of the war\nin literature and art, evaluations of heroes and villains, and considerations\nof the moral and political lessons of the war.[269] The last theme includes\nmoral evaluations of racism and slavery, heroism in combat and behind the\nlines, and the issues of democracy and minority rights, as well as the notion\nof an \"Empire_of_Liberty\" influencing the world.[270]\nDeeply religious Southerners saw the hand of God in history, which demonstrated\nHis wrath at their sinfulness, or His rewards for their suffering. Historian\nWilson Fallin has examined the sermons of white and black Baptist preachers\nafter the War. Southern white preachers said:\n     God had chastised them and given them a special mission _ to\n     maintain orthodoxy, strict biblicism, personal piety, and traditional\n     race relations. Slavery, they insisted, had not been sinful. Rather,\n     emancipation was a historical tragedy and the end of Reconstruction\n     was a clear sign of God\'s favor.\nIn sharp contrast, Black preachers interpreted the Civil War as:\n     God\'s gift of freedom. They appreciated opportunities to exercise\n     their independence, to worship in their own way, to affirm their\n     worth and dignity, and to proclaim the fatherhood of God and the\n     brotherhood of man. Most of all, they could form their own churches,\n     associations, and conventions. These institutions offered self&#8211;help\n     and racial uplift, and provided places where the gospel of liberation\n     could be proclaimed. As a result, black preachers continued to insist\n     that God would protect and help him; God would be their rock in a\n     stormy land.[271]\n\n<i> Lost Cause \n</i>\n\nSee also: Neo&#8211;Confederate\nMemory of the war in the white South crystallized in the myth of the \"Lost\nCause\", shaping regional identity and race relations for generations.[272] Alan\nT. Nolan notes that the Lost Cause was expressly \"a rationalization, a cover&#8211;up\nto vindicate the name and fame\" of those in rebellion. Some claims revolve\naround the insignificance of slavery; some appeals highlight cultural\ndifferences between North and South; the military conflict by Confederate\nactors is idealized; in any case, secession was said to be lawful.[273] The two\nimportant political legacies that flowed from the adoption of the Lost Cause\nanalysis were that it facilitated the reunification of the North and the South,\nand it excused the \"virulent racism\" of the 19th century, sacrificing African&#8211;\nAmerican progress to a white man\'s reunification. But the Lost Cause legacy to\nhistory is \"a caricature of the truth. This caricature wholly misrepresents and\ndistorts the facts of the matter\" in every instance.[274]\nBeginning in 1961 the U.S. Post Office released Commemorative_stamps for five\nfamous battles, each issued on the 100th anniversary of the respective battle.\n\n<i> Beardian historiography \n</i>\n\nThe interpretation of the Civil War presented by Charles_A._Beard and Mary R.\nBeard in The Rise of American Civilization (1927) was highly influential among\nhistorians and the general public until the civil rights era of the 1950s. The\nBeards downplayed slavery, abolitionism, and issues of morality. They ignored\nconstitutional issues of states\' rights and even ignored American nationalism\nas the force that finally led to victory in the war. Indeed, the ferocious\ncombat itself was passed over as merely an ephemeral event. Much more important\nwas the calculus of class conflict. The Beards announced that the Civil War was\nreally a:\n     Social cataclysm in which the capitalists, laborers, and farmers of\n     the North and West drove from power in the national government the\n     planting aristocracy of the South.\"[275]\nThe Beards themselves abandoned their interpretation by the 1940s and it became\ndefunct among historians in the 1950s, when scholars shifted to an emphasis on\nslavery. However, Beardian themes still echo among Lost Cause writers.[276]\n\n<i> Civil War commemoration \n</i>\n\nMain article: Commemoration_of_the_American_Civil_War\nSee also: Commemoration_of_the_American_Civil_War_on_postage_stamps\nGrand Army of the Republic (Union)\nUnited Confederate Veterans\nThe American Civil War has been commemorated in many capacities ranging from\nthe reenactment of battles, to statues and memorial halls erected, to films\nbeing produced, to stamps and coins with Civil War themes being issued, all of\nwhich helped to shape public memory. This varied advent occurred in greater\nproportions on the 100th and 150th anniversary. [277] Hollywood\'s take on the\nwar has been especially influential in shaping public memory, as seen in such\nfilm classics as Birth_of_a_Nation (1915), Gone_with_the_Wind (1939), and more\nrecently Lincoln (2012).\n\n<u> See also \n</u>\n\n[Portal_icon] American_Civil_War_portal\nGeneral reference\n    * Battles_of_the\n      American_Civil_War\n    * Bibliography_of\n      the_American_Civil\n      War\n    * Corps_badges_of\n      the_American_Civil\n      War\n    * Costliest_Battles\n      of_the_American\n      Civil_War\n    * Naval_bibliography\n      of_the_American\n      Civil_War\n    * Origins_of_the\n      American_Civil_War\n    * Uniforms_of_the    Topical articles\n      Confederacy            * Blockade_runners_of_the_American_Civil_War\n    * Uniforms_of_the        * Blockade,_Union___of_the_American_Civil_War\n      Union                  * Casualties_in_the_American_Civil_War\n    * Weapons_in_the         * Commemoration_of_the_American_Civil_War\n      American_Civil_War     * Commemoration_of_the_American_Civil_War_on\nUnion                          postage_stamps\n    * United_States          * Infantry_in_the_American_Civil_War\n    * Union_Army             * Nursing_in_the_American_Civil_War,_Dorothea_Dix\n    * Union_Navy             * Ships_captured_during_the_American_Civil_War\nConfederacy                  * Slaves_and_the_American_Civil_War\n    * Confederate_States     * Spies_in_the_American_Civil_War\n    * Confederate_Army   National articles\n    * Confederate_Navy       * Foreign_enlistment_in_the_American_Civil_War\nEthnic articles              * Britain_in_the_American_Civil_War\n    * African_Americans      * Canada_in_the_American_Civil_War\n      in_the_American\n      Civil_War\n    * German_Americans\n      in_the_American\n      Civil_War\n    * Hispanic_Americans\n      in_the_American\n      Civil_War\n    * Irish_Americans_in\n      the_American_Civil\n      War\n    * Italian_Americans\n      in_the_American\n      Civil_War\n    * Native_Americans\n      in_the_American\n      Civil_War\n\n<u> References \n</u>\n\nNotes\n   1. ^ Territories are organized areas that could potentially become states.\n   2. ^ A novel way of calculating casualties by looking at the deviation of\n      the death rate of men of fighting age from the norm through analysis of\n      census data found that at least 627,000 and at most 888,000 people, but\n      most likely 761,000 people, died through the war.[10]\n   3. ^ As sectional divisions hardened, support for breaking up the Democratic\n      party and secession on the issue of slavery in the territories was\n      strongly correlated to the number of plantations in each region. Lipset\n      looked at the secessionist vote in each Southern state in 1860_61. In\n      each state he divided the counties into high, medium or low proportion of\n      slaves. He found that in the 181 high&#8211;slavery counties, the vote was 72 percent\n      for secession. In the 205 low&#8211;slavery counties, the vote was only 37 percent for\n      secession. (And in the 153 middle counties, the vote for secession was in\n      the middle at 60 percent.) States of the Deep_South, which had the greatest\n      concentration of plantations, were the first to secede. The upper South\n      slave states of Virginia, North_Carolina, Arkansas and Tennessee had\n      fewer plantations, and rejected secession until the Fort_Sumter crisis\n      forced them to choose sides. Border states had fewer plantations still\n      and never seceded.[28][29][30] Maps on p. 101 (The Southern Economy) and\n      p. 236 (The Progress of Secession) are also relevant.[31]\n   4. ^ Abraham Lincoln, Speech at New Haven, Conn., March 6, 1860. The slavery\n      issue was related to sectional competition for control of the\n      territories.[39] The Southern demand for a slave_code for the territories\n      was the issue used by Southern politicians to split the Democratic Party\n      in two, which all but guaranteed the election of Lincoln and secession.\n      When secession was an issue, South Carolina planter and state Senator\n      John Townsend said that, \"our enemies are about to take possession of the\n      Government, that they intend to rule us according to the caprices of\n      their fanatical theories, and according to the declared purposes of\n      abolishing slavery\". See John Townsend, The Doom of Slavery in the Union,\n      its Safety out of it, October 29, 1860. Similar opinions were expressed\n      throughout the South in editorials, political speeches and declarations\n      of reasons for secession. Even though Lincoln had no plans to outlaw\n      slavery where it existed, whites throughout the South expressed fears for\n      the future of slavery.[40]\n   5. ^ Before 1850, slave owners controlled the presidency for fifty years,\n      the Speaker\'s chair for forty&#8211;one years, and the chairmanship of the\n      House Ways and Means Committee that set tariffs for forty&#8211;two years,\n      while 18 of 31 Supreme Court justices owned slaves.[63]\n   6. ^ \"Union population 1864\" aggregates 1860 population, average annual\n      immigration 1855_1864, and population governed formerly by CSA per\n      Kenneth Martis source. Contrabands and after the Emancipation\n      Proclamation freedmen, migrating into Union control on the coasts and to\n      the advancing armies, and natural increase are excluded.\n   7. ^ \"Slave 1864, CSA\" aggregates 1860 slave census of VA, NC, SC, GA and\n      TX. It omits losses from contraband and after the Emancipation\n      Proclamation, freedmen migrating to the Union controlled coastal ports\n      and those joining advancing Union armies, especially in the Mississippi\n      Valley.\n   8. ^ At the beginning of the war, some Union commanders thought they were\n      supposed to return escaped slaves to their masters. By 1862, when it\n      became clear that this would be a long war, the question of what to do\n      about slavery became more general. The Southern economy and military\n      effort depended on slave labor. It began to seem unreasonable to protect\n      slavery while blockading Southern commerce and destroying Southern\n      production. As one Congressman put it, the slaves \"&#8230; cannot be neutral.\n      As laborers, if not as soldiers, they will be allies of the rebels, or of\n      the Union.\"[248] The same Congressman_and his fellow Radical\n      Republicans_put pressure on Lincoln to rapidly emancipate the slaves,\n      whereas moderate Republicans came to accept gradual, compensated\n      emancipation and colonization.[249] Enslaved African Americans did not\n      wait for Lincoln\'s action before escaping and seeking freedom behind\n      Union lines. From early years of the war, hundreds of thousands of\n      African Americans escaped to Union lines, especially in occupied areas\n      like Nashville, Norfolk and the Hampton Roads region in 1862, Tennessee\n      from 1862 on, the line of Sherman\'s march, etc. So many African Americans\n      fled to Union lines that commanders created camps and schools for them,\n      where both adults and children learned to read and write. See Catton,\n      Bruce. Never Call Retreat, p. 335. The American Missionary Association\n      entered the war effort by sending teachers south to such contraband\n      camps, for instance establishing schools in Norfolk and on nearby\n      plantations. In addition, approximately 180,000 or more African&#8211;American\n      men served as soldiers and sailors with Union troops. Most of those were\n      escaped slaves. Probably the most prominent of these African&#8211;American\n      soldiers is the 54th_Massachusetts_Volunteer_Infantry.\n   9. ^ In spite of the South\'s shortage of soldiers, most Southern leaders _\n      until 1865 _ opposed enlisting slaves. They used them as laborers to\n      support the war effort. As Howell_Cobb said, \"If slaves will make good\n      soldiers our whole theory of slavery is wrong.\" Confederate generals\n      Patrick_Cleburne and Robert_E._Lee argued in favor of arming blacks late\n      in the war, and Jefferson_Davis was eventually persuaded to support plans\n      for arming slaves to avoid military defeat. The Confederacy surrendered\n      at Appomattox before this plan could be implemented.[250] The great\n      majority of the 4 million slaves were freed by the Emancipation\n      Proclamation, as Union armies moved south. Historian John_D._Winters\n      referred to the exhilaration of the slaves when the Union Army came\n      through Louisiana: \"As the troops moved up to Alexandria, the Negroes\n      crowded the roadsides to watch the passing army. They were \'all frantic\n      with joy, some weeping, some blessing, and some dancing in the exuberance\n      of their emotions.\' All of the Negroes were attracted by the pageantry\n      and excitement of the army. Others cheered because they anticipated the\n      freedom to plunder and to do as they pleased now that the Federal troops\n      were there.\"[251] Confederates enslaved captured black Union soldiers,\n      and black soldiers especially were shot when trying to surrender at the\n      Fort_Pillow_Massacre. See Catton, Bruce. Never Call Retreat, p. 335. This\n      led to a breakdown of the prisoner_and_mail_exchange_program and the\n      growth of prison camps such as Andersonville_prison in Georgia, where\n      almost 13,000 Union prisoners of war died of starvation and disease.[252]\nCitations\n   1. ^ a b \"The_Belligerent_Rights_of_the_Rebels_at_an_End._All_Nations_Warned\n      Against_Harboring_Their_Privateers._If_They_Do_Their_Ships_Will_be\n      Excluded_from_Our_Ports._Restoration_of_Law_in_the_State_of_Virginia._The\n      Machinery_of_Government_to_be_Put_in_Motion_There.\". The New York Times.\n      The_New_York_Times_Company. Associated_Press. May 10, 1865. Retrieved\n      December 23, 2013. \n   2. ^ a b c d e f Fox, William F. Regimental_losses_in_the_American_Civil_War\n      (1889)\n   3. ^ a b c d Official_DOD_data\n   4. ^ Chambers_1999, p. 849.\n   5. ^ Recounting_the_dead, Associate Professor J. David Hacker, \"estimates,\n      based on Census data, indicate that the death toll was approximately\n      750,000, and may have been as high as 850,000\"\n   6. ^ \"Date_of_Secession_Related_to_1860_Black_Population\", America\'s Civil\n      War\n   7. ^ a b c \"Teaching_American_History_in_Maryland___Documents_for_the\n      Classroom:_Arrest_of_the_Maryland_Legislature,_1861\". Maryland State\n      Archives. 2005. Archived from the original on January 11, 2008. Retrieved\n      February 6, 2008. \n   8. ^ Jones_1999, p. 154.\n   9. ^ Frank J. Williams, \"Doing Less and Doing More: The President and the\n      Proclamation_Legally, Militarily and Politically,\" in Harold Holzer,\n      ed. The Emancipation Proclamation (2006) pp. 74_5.\n  10. ^ Hacker_2011, p. 307&#8211;348.\n  11. ^ Huddleston_2002, p. 3.\n  12. ^ The American Civil War. By Garry.W.Gallagher, Stephen D Engle, Robert K\n      Krick &amp; Joseph T Glatthaar. Forward By Joseph M. McPherson\n  13. ^ James C. Bradford, A companion to American military history (2010) vol.\n      1, p. 101\n  14. ^ See sections below this introduction, including citations in these\n      four: Freehling, William W., The Road to Disunion: Secessionists\n      Triumphant 1854_1861, pp. 9_24, and Martis, Kenneth C., \"The\n      Historical Atlas of Political Parties in the United States Congress,\n      1789_1989\", ISBN_0&#8211;02&#8211;920170&#8211;5, p. 111_115, and Foner, Eric. Politics\n      and Ideology in the Age of the Civil War, Oxford U. Press, 1980 ISBN_0&#8211;\n      19&#8211;502781&#8211;7, p. 18_20, 21_24, and Eskridge, Larry (January 29, 2011).\n      \"After 150 years, we still ask: Why \'this cruel war\'?.\". Canton Daily\n      Ledger (Canton, Illinois). Retrieved January 29, 2011.\n  15. ^ Green_2008, p. 291.\n  16. ^ Weeks_2013, p. 240.\n  17. ^ Olsen_2002, p. 237.\n  18. ^ Brunell_2011, p. 136.\n  19. ^ Gienapp, William E., \"The Crisis of American Democracy: The Political\n      System and the Coming of the Civil War\" in Boritt ed. Why the Civil War\n      Came 79_123. See also Eric Foner, Free Soil, Free Labor, Free Men: The\n      Ideology of the Republican Party before the Civil War (2nd ed. 1995),\n      pp. 311_12.\n  20. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 88_91.\n  21. ^ In Gerson, Harriet Beecher Stowe, p. 68; See also Stowe, Key to Uncle\n      Tom\'s Cabin (1953), p. 39.\n  22. ^ a b Guelzo_2009, p. 61.\n  23. ^ Foner_2010, p. 100.\n  24. ^ William W. Freehling, The Road to Disunion: Secessionists Triumphant\n      1854_1861, pp. 9_24. Such fears greatly increased Southern efforts to\n      make Kansas a slave state. By 1860, the number of white border state\n      families owning slaves plunged to only 16 percent of the total. Slaves\n      sold to lower South states were owned by a smaller number of wealthy\n      slave owners as the price of slaves increased.\n  25. ^ Eugene D. Genovese, The Political Economy of Slavery: Studies in the\n      Economy and Society of the Slave South (Wesleyan U.P,. 1988). p. 244\n  26. ^ Manisha Sinha, The Counterrevolution of Slavery: Politics and Ideology\n      in Antebellum South Carolina (2000), pp. 127_8. Failing that, their\n      1854 Ostend_Manifesto was an unsuccessful attempt to annex Cuba as a\n      slave state. See Potter, David. The Impending Crisis, pp. 201_204.\n  27. ^ Lipset_1960, p. 349.\n  28. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 242.\n  29. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 255.\n  30. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 282_283.\n  31. ^ Potter_1976, pp. 503_505.\n  32. ^ \"Vote_fraud_in_Kansas\". Retrieved October 4, 2014. \n  33. ^ Potter_1976, p. 299&#8211;327.\n  34. ^ See Williamjames Hoffer, The Caning of Charles Sumner: Honor, Idealism,\n      and the Origins of the Civil War (2010), pp. 62, 131_33.\n  35. ^ Fehrenbacher_1981, p. 208.\n  36. ^ Potter_1976, p. 275.\n  37. ^ Foner, Eric. \'Free Soil, Free Labor, Free Men: The Ideology of the\n      Republican Party before the Civil War (2nd ed. 1995), pp. 311_12.\n  38. ^ Potter_1976, p. 356&#8211;384.\n  39. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 195.\n  40. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 243.\n  41. ^ Martis, Kenneth C., \"The Historical Atlas of Political Parties in the\n      United States Congress, 1789_1989\", ISBN_0&#8211;02&#8211;920170&#8211;5, p. 111_115.\n      Though elected in November by the Electoral College with a plurality of\n      popular votes, he was certified Constitutionally elected President by\n      Congress in December before the Republican majorities were seated. Both\n      Lincoln and the Republican Platform guaranteed no interference with\n      slavery where it existed, and in his Inaugural Address he supported the\n      proposed Corwin_Amendment to Constitutionally restate it. But\n      secessionists claimed that such guarantees were meaningless. They feared\n      that Republicans would use patronage to incite slaves and antislavery\n      Southern whites such as Hinton_Rowan_Helper. Then they feared slavery in\n      the lower South, like a \"scorpion encircled by fire would sting itself to\n      death\". See Freehling, William W., The Road to Disunion: Secessionists\n      Triumphant 1854_1861, pp. 9_24. Besides the loss of Kansas to free\n      soil Northerners, secessionists feared that the loss of slaves in the\n      border states would lead to emancipation, and that upper South slave\n      states might be the next dominoes to fall.\n  42. ^ Schott_1996, p. 334.\n  43. ^ \"The_War_of_Northern_Aggression_&#8211;_Jacobin\". Retrieved October 4, 2014. \n  44. ^ \"The_War_of_Southern_Aggression_by_James_M._McPherson\". Retrieved\n      October 4, 2014. \n  45. ^ Eskridge, Larry (January 29, 2011). \"After_150_years,_we_still_ask:_Why\n      \'this_cruel_war\'?.\". Canton Daily Ledger (Canton, Illinois). Retrieved\n      January 29, 2011.  \"The power of the federal government to affect the\n      institution of slavery, specifically limiting it in newly added\n      territories\" was the primary political debate in Southern states over\n      secession, rather than states\' rights in general.\n  46. ^ Foner_1981, pp. 18_20, 21_24.\n  47. ^ a b Forrest McDonald, States\' Rights and the Union: Imperium in\n      Imperio, 1776_1876 (2002)\n  48. ^ McPherson_2007, pp. 3_9.\n  49. ^ Charles S. Sydnor, The Development of Southern Sectionalism 1819_1848\n      (1948).\n  50. ^ Robert Royal Russel, Economic Aspects of Southern Sectionalism,\n      1840_1861 (1973).\n  51. ^ Adam Rothman, Slave Country: American Expansion and the Origins of the\n      Deep South (2005).\n  52. ^ Catton_1960, p. 8.\n  53. ^ Kenneth M. Stampp, The Imperiled Union: Essays on the Background of the\n      Civil War (1981) p. 198; Richard Hofstadter, The Progressive Historians:\n      Turner, Beard, Parrington (1969).\n  54. ^ Woodworth_1996, p. 145, 151, 505, 512, 554, 557,684.\n  55. ^ Clement Eaton, Freedom of Thought in the Old South (1940)\n  56. ^ John Hope Franklin, The Militant South 1800_1861 (1956).\n  57. ^ Abraham Lincoln, Cooper Union Address, New York, February 27, 1860.\n  58. ^ Ahlstrom_1972, p. 648&#8211;649.\n  59. ^ James McPherson, \"Antebellum Southern Exceptionalism: A New Look at an\n      Old Question,\" Civil War History 29 (September 1983).\n  60. ^ Thornton_&amp;_Ekelund_2004, p. 21.\n  61. ^ Frank Taussig, The Tariff History of the United States (1931),\n      pp. 115_61\n  62. ^ Hofstadter_1938, p. 50&#8211;55.\n  63. ^ a b Richards_2000, p. 1&#8211;9.\n  64. ^ Eric Foner, Free Soil, Free Labor, Free Men: The Ideology of the\n      Republican Party before the Civil War (1970).\n  65. ^ Bolton_1993, p. 67.\n  66. ^ McPherson_2007, p. 14.\n  67. ^ Stampp_1990, p. 190&#8211;193.\n  68. ^ Krannawitter_2008, p. 49&#8211;50.\n  69. ^ McPherson_2007, pp. 13_14.\n  70. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 17&#8211;18.\n  71. ^ Guelzo_2012, p. 21&#8211;22.\n  72. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 15.\n  73. ^ Miller_2008, p. 153.\n  74. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 19.\n  75. ^ McPherson_2007, p. 16.\n  76. ^ Bestor_1964, pp. 19&#8211;21.\n  77. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 20.\n  78. ^ Russell_1966, p. 468&#8211;469.\n  79. ^ Bestor_1964, pp. 20&#8211;21.\n  80. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 21.\n  81. ^ Bestor_1964, pp. 21&#8211;23.\n  82. ^ Johannsen_1973, p. 406.\n  83. ^ \"Territorial_Politics_and_Government\". Territorial Kansas Online:\n      University of Kansas and Kansas Historical Society. Retrieved July 10,\n      2014. \n  84. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 23.\n  85. ^ Varon_2008, p. 58.\n  86. ^ Russell_1966, p. 470.\n  87. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 23&#8211;24.\n  88. ^ Holt_2005, p. 34&#8211;35.\n  89. ^ McPherson_2007, p. 7.\n  90. ^ Krannawitter_2008, p. 232.\n  91. ^ Gara, 1964, p. 190\n  92. ^ Bestor_1964, p. 24&#8211;25.\n  93. ^ Potter_1962, p. 924&#8211;950.\n  94. ^ C. Vann Woodward (1971), American Counterpoint: Slavery and Racism in\n      the North&#8211;South Dialogue, p.281.\n  95. ^ Bertram Wyatt&#8211;Brown, The Shaping of Southern Culture: Honor, Grace, and\n      War, 1760s_1880s (2000).\n  96. ^ Avery Craven, The Growth of Southern Nationalism, 1848_1861 (1953).\n  97. ^ \"Republican Platform of 1860,\" in Kirk H. Porter, and Donald Bruce\n      Johnson, eds. National Party Platforms, 1840_1956, (University of\n      Illinois Press, 1956) p. 32.\n  98. ^ Susan&#8211;Mary Grant, North over South: Northern Nationalism and American\n      Identity in the Antebellum Era (2000); Melinda Lawson, Patriot Fires:\n      Forging a New American Nationalism in the Civil War North (2005).\n  99. ^ Potter_1976, p. 485.\n 100. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 24.\n 101. ^ President_James_Buchanan,_Message_of_December_8,_1860. Retrieved\n      November 28, 2012.\n 102. ^ \"Profile_Showing_the_Grades_upon_the_Different_Routes_Surveyed_for_the\n      Union_Pacific_Rail_Road_Between_the_Missouri_River_and_the_Valley_of_the\n      Platte_River\". World_Digital_Library. 1865. Retrieved July 16, 2013. \n 103. ^ Guisepi, Robert. \"The_American_Civil_War,_Confederate_States_of\n      America\". history_world.org. Retrieved December 9, 2014. \n 104. ^ Ordinances_of_Secession_by_State. Retrieved November 28, 2012.\n 105. ^ The text of the_Declaration_of_the_Immediate_Causes_Which_Induce_and\n      Justify_the_Secession_of_South_Carolina_from_the_Federal_Union.\n 106. ^ The text of A_Declaration_of_the_Immediate_Causes_which_Induce_and\n      Justify_the_Secession_of_the_State_of_Mississippi_from_the_Federal_Union.\n      Retrieved November 28, 2012.\n 107. ^ The text of Georgia\'s_secession_declaration. Retrieved November 28,\n      2012.\n 108. ^ The text of A_Declaration_of_the_Causes_which_Impel_the_State_of_Texas\n      to_Secede_from_the_Federal_Union. Retrieved November 28, 2012.\n 109. ^ Annual_Register&#8230;_for_1861 (1862) pp.233&#8211;239\n 110. ^ Arrell_1981, p. 117&#8211;120.\n 111. ^ \"United_States_Volunteers___Indian_Troops\". civilwararchive.com.\n      January 28, 2008. Retrieved August 10, 2008. \n 112. ^ \"Civil_War_Refugees\". Oklahoma_Historical_Society. Oklahoma_State\n      University. Retrieved August 10, 2008. \n 113. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 284&#8211;287.\n 114. ^ William C. Harris, Lincoln and the Border States: Preserving the Union\n      (University Press of Kansas, 2011) p 71\n 115. ^ Howard, F. K. (Frank Key) (1863). Fourteen_Months_in_American_Bastiles.\n      London: H.F. Mackintosh. Retrieved August 18, 2014. \n 116. ^ Nevins, The War for the Union (1959) 1:119&#8211;29.\n 117. ^ Nevins, The War for the Union (1959) 1:129&#8211;36.\n 118. ^ \"A_State_of_Convenience,_The_Creation_of_West_Virginia\". West Virginia\n      Archives &amp; History. Retrieved April 20, 2012. \n 119. ^ Curry, Richard Orr (1964), A House Divided, A Study of the Statehood\n      Politics &amp; the Copperhead Movement in West Virginia, Univ. of\n      Pittsburgh Press, map on page 49.\n 120. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 303.\n 121. ^ Weigley_2000, p. 55.\n 122. ^ Snell, Mark A., West Virginia and the Civil War, History Press,\n      Charleston, SC, 2011, pg. 28\n 123. ^ Neely_1993, p. 10&#8211;11.\n 124. ^ a b McPherson_1988, pp. 234_266.\n 125. ^ Schouler_1899, p. ?.\n 126. ^ Abraham Lincoln, First Inaugural Address, Monday, March 4, 1861.\n 127. ^ Lincoln, First Inaugural Address, March 4, 1861.\n 128. ^ a b Potter_1976, p. 572&#8211;573.\n 129. ^ Allan Nevins, The War for the Union: The Improvised War 1861&#8211;1862\n      (1959) pp 74&#8211;75\n 130. ^ Russell McClintock, Lincoln and the Decision for War: The Northern\n      Response to Secession (2008) pp 254&#8211;74 provides details of support across\n      the North. online\n 131. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 274.\n 132. ^ Howard Louis Conard (1901). Encyclopedia_of_the_History_of_Missouri.\n      p. 45. \n 133. ^ \"Abraham_Lincoln:_Proclamation_83___Increasing_the_Size_of_the_Army\n      and_Navy\". Presidency.ucsb.edu. Retrieved November 3, 2011. \n 134. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 276_307.\n 135. ^ Keegan, \"The American Civil War\", p.73. Over 10,000 military\n      engagements took place during the war, 40 percent of them in Virginia and\n      Tennessee. See Gabor Boritt, ed. War Comes Again (1995), p. 247.\n 136. ^ \"With an actual strength of 1,080 officers and 14,926 enlisted men on\n      June 30, 1860, the Regular Army &#8230;\" Civil_War_Extracts p. 199_221,\n      American Military History.\n 137. ^ E. Merton Coulter, Confederate States of America (1950) p.308. John G.\n      Nicolay and John Hay, (Abraham_Lincoln:_a_history, vol. 4, p. 264) state:\n      \"Since the organization of the Montgomery government in February, some\n      four different calls for Southern volunteers had been made &#8230; In his\n      message of April 29 to the rebel Congress, Jefferson Davis proposed to\n      organize for instant action an army of 100,000 &#8230;\" Coulter reports that\n      Alexander Stephens took this to mean Davis wanted unilateral control of a\n      standing army, and from that moment on became his implacable opponent.\n 138. ^ Albert Burton Moore. Conscription and Conflict in the Confederacy\n      (1924) online_edition.\n 139. ^ Albert Bernhardt Faust, The_German_Element_in_the_United_States (1909)\n      v._1,_p._523_online. The railroads and banks grew rapidly. See\n      Oberholtzer,_Ellis_Paxson. Jay_Cooke:_Financier_Of_The_Civil_War,_(1907)\n      Vol._2 at Google_Books, pp. 378_430. See also Oberholtzer, A History of\n      the United States Since the Civil War (1926) 3:69_122.\n 140. ^ Barnet Schecter, The Devil\'s Own Work: The Civil War Draft Riots and\n      the Fight to Reconstruct America (2007).\n 141. ^ Eugene Murdock, One million men: the Civil War draft in the North\n      (1971).\n 142. ^ Judith Lee Hallock, \"The Role of the Community in Civil War Desertion.\"\n      Civil War History (1983) 29#2 pp: 123&#8211;134. online\n 143. ^ Peter S. Bearman, \"Desertion as localism: Army unit solidarity and\n      group norms in the US Civil War.\" Social Forces (1991) 70#2 pp: 321&#8211;342\n      in_JSTOR.\n 144. ^ Robert Fantina, Desertion and the American soldier, 1776_2006 (2006),\n      p. 74\n 145. ^ Keegan_2009, p. 57.\n 146. ^ Perman_2011, p. 177.\n 147. ^ Roger Pickenpaugh (2013). Captives_in_Blue:_The_Civil_War_Prisons_of\n      the_Confederacy. University of Alabama Press. pp. 57_73. \n 148. ^ Spencer C. Tucker, ed. (2013). American_Civil_War:_The_Definitive\n      Encyclopedia_and_Document_Collection. ABC&#8211;CLIO. p. 1466. \n 149. ^ Welles_1865, p. 152.\n 150. ^ Tucker_2010, p. 462.\n 151. ^ Canney_1998, p. ?.\n 152. ^ Richter_2009, p. 49.\n 153. ^ Johnson_1998, p. 228.\n 154. ^ Anderson_1989, p. 288&#8211;289, 296_298.\n 155. ^ Nelson_2005, p. 92.\n 156. ^ a b Anderson_1989, p. 300.\n 157. ^ Gerald F. Teaster and Linda and James Treaster Ambrose, The Confederate\n      Submarine H. L. Hunley (1989)\n 158. ^ Nelson_2005, p. 345.\n 159. ^ Fuller_2008, p. 36.\n 160. ^ Mark E. Neely, Jr. \"The Perils of Running the Blockade: The Influence\n      of International Law in an Era of Total War,\" Civil War History (1986)\n      32#2, pp. 101_118 in_Project_MUSE\n 161. ^ Stephen R. Wise, Lifeline of the Confederacy: Blockade Running during\n      the Civil War (1991)\n 162. ^ Surdam, David G. (1998). \"The Union Navy\'s blockade reconsidered\".\n      Naval War College Review 51 (4): 85_107. \n 163. ^ David G. Surdam, Northern Naval Superiority and the Economics of the\n      American Civil War (University of South Carolina Press, 2001)\n 164. ^ Jones_2002, p. 225.\n 165. ^ Anderson_1989, p. 91.\n 166. ^ Whitsell, Robert D. (1963). \"Military and Naval Activity between Cairo\n      and Columbus\". Register of the Kentucky Historical Society 62 (2):\n      107_121. \n 167. ^ Myron J. Smith, Tinclads in the Civil War: Union Light&#8211;Draught Gunboat\n      Operations on Western Waters, 1862_1865 (2009)\n 168. ^ Frank_2003, p. 170.\n 169. ^ Symonds_2001, p. 92.\n 170. ^ Ronald Scott Mangum, \"The Vicksburg Campaign: A Study In Joint\n      Operations,\" Parameters: U.S. Army War College (1991) 21#3, pp. 74_86\n      online\n 171. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 339_345.\n 172. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 342.\n 173. ^ Foote_1974, p. 464&#8211;519.\n 174. ^ Bruce Catton, Terrible Swift Sword, pp. 263_296.\n 175. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 424_427.\n 176. ^ a b McPherson_1988, pp. 538_544.\n 177. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 528_533.\n 178. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 543_545.\n 179. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 557_558.\n 180. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 571_574.\n 181. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 639_645.\n 182. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 653_663.\n 183. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 664.\n 184. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 404_405.\n 185. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 418_420.\n 186. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 419_420.\n 187. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 480_483.\n 188. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 405_413.\n 189. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 637_638.\n 190. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 677_680.\n 191. ^ a b Keegan_2009, p. 270.\n 192. ^ Keegan_2009, p. 100.\n 193. ^ James B. Martin, Third War: Irregular Warfare on the Western Border\n      1861_1865 (Combat Studies Institute Leavenworth Paper series, number\n      23, 2012). See also, Michael Fellman, Inside War: The Guerrilla Conflict\n      in Missouri during the Civil War (1989). Missouri alone was the scene of\n      over 1,000 engagements between regular units, and uncounted numbers of\n      guerrilla attacks and raids by informal pro&#8211;Confederate bands, especially\n      in the recently settled western counties.\n 194. ^ Bohl, Sarah (2004). \"A War on Civilians: Order Number 11 and the\n      Evacuation of Western Missouri\". Prologue 36 (1): 44_51. \n 195. ^ Graves, William H. (1991). \"Indian Soldiers for the Gray Army:\n      Confederate Recruitment in Indian Territory\". Chronicles of Oklahoma 69\n      (2): 134_145. \n 196. ^ Neet, J. Frederick; Jr (1996). \"Stand Watie: Confederate General in the\n      Cherokee Nation\". Great Plains Journal 6 (1): 36_51. \n 197. ^ Keegan_2009, p. 220&#8211;221.\n 198. ^ Mark E. Neely Jr.; \"Was the Civil War a Total War?\" Civil War History,\n      Vol. 50, 2004, pp. 434+\n 199. ^ U.S. Grant (1990). Personal Memoirs of U.S. Grant; Selected Letters.\n      Library of America. p. 247. ISBN 0&#8211;940450&#8211;58&#8211;5. \n 200. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 724_735.\n 201. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 741_742.\n 202. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 778_779.\n 203. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 773_776.\n 204. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 812_815.\n 205. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 825_830.\n 206. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 846_847.\n 207. ^ William Marvel, Lee\'s Last Retreat: The Flight to Appomattox (2002) pp.\n      158_81.\n 208. ^ Unaware of the surrender of Lee, on April 16 the last major battles of\n      the war were fought at the Battle_of_Columbus,_Georgia and the Battle_of\n      West_Point.\n 209. ^ Morris, John Wesley, Ghost towns of Oklahoma, University of Oklahoma\n      Press, 1977, pp. 68_69, ISBN_0&#8211;8061&#8211;1420&#8211;7\n 210. ^ a b c McPherson_1988, pp. 546_557.\n 211. ^ a b Herring_2011, p. 237.\n 212. ^ a b McPherson_1988, p. 386.\n 213. ^ Allan Nevins, War for the Union 1862_1863, pp. 263_264.\n 214. ^ a b Stephen_B._Oates, The Approaching Fury: Voices of the Storm\n      1820_1861, p. 125.\n 215. ^ Herring_2011, p. 261.\n 216. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 855.\n 217. ^ a b James McPherson, Why did the Confederacy Lose?. p. ?.\n 218. ^ Railroad length is from: Chauncey_Depew (ed.), One Hundred Years of\n      American Commerce 1795_1895, p. 111; For other data see: 1860_US_census\n      and Carter, Susan B., ed. The Historical Statistics of the United States:\n      Millennial Edition (5 vols), 2006.\n 219. ^ Martis, Kenneth C., \"The Historical Atlas of the Congresses of the\n      Confederate States of America: 1861_1865\" Simon &amp; Schuster (1994)\n      ISBN_0&#8211;13&#8211;389115&#8211;1 pp.27. At the beginning of 1865, the Confederacy\n      controlled one&#8211;third of its congressional districts, which were\n      apportioned by population. The major slave&#8211;populations found in\n      Louisiana, Mississippi, Tennessee, and Alabama were effectively under\n      Union control by the end of 1864.\n 220. ^ Digital History Reader, U.S._Railroad_Construction,_1860_1880\n      Virginia Tech, Retrieved August 21, 2012. \"Total Union railroad miles\"\n      aggregates existing track reported 1860 AT 21800 plus new construction\n      1860_1864 AT 5000, plus southern railroads administered by USMRR AT 2300.\n 221. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 771_772.\n 222. ^ Murray_1996, p. 235.\n 223. ^ Heidler_2002, p. 1207_1210.\n 224. ^ Ward_1990, p. 272.\n 225. ^ E. Merton Coulter, The Confederate States of America, 1861_1865\n      (1950) p. 566\n 226. ^ Richard E. Beringer, Herman Hattaway, Archer Jones and William N. Still\n      Jr., Why the South Lost the Civil War (1991) ch 1\n 227. ^ Armstead Robinson, Bitter Fruits of Bondage: The Demise of Slavery and\n      the Collapse of the Confederacy, 1861_1865 (University of Virginia\n      Press, 2004)\n 228. ^ see Alan Farmer, History_Review_(2005)_No._52:_15_20.\n 229. ^ McPherson_1997, pp. 169_172.\n 230. ^ Gallagher_1999, p. 57.\n 231. ^ Fehrenbacher, Don (2004). \"Lincoln\'s_Wartime_Leadership:_The_First\n      Hundred_Days\". University of Illinois. Retrieved October 16, 2007. \n 232. ^ Don H. Doyle, The Cause of All Nations: An International History of the\n      American Civil War (2014)\n 233. ^ Fergus M. Bordewich, \"The World Was Watching: America\'s Civil War\n      slowly came to be seen as part of a global struggle against oppressive\n      privilege,\" Wall_Street_Journal_(Feb._7&#8211;8,_2015)\n 234. ^ Nofi,_Al (June 13, 2001). \"Statistics_on_the_War\'s_Costs\". Louisiana\n      State University. Archived from the_original on July 11, 2007. Retrieved\n      October 14, 2007. \n 235. ^ \"U.S._Civil_War_Took_Bigger_Toll_Than_Previously_Estimated,_New\n      Analysis_Suggests\". Science Daily. September 22, 2011. Retrieved\n      September 22, 2011. \n 236. ^ Hacker, J. David (September 20, 2011). \"Recounting_the_Dead\". The New\n      York Times (The_New_York_Times_Company). Associated_Press. Retrieved\n      September 22, 2011. \n 237. ^ McPherson_1988, p. xix.\n 238. ^ Vinovskis_1990, p. 7.\n 239. ^ Richard Wightman Fox (2008).\"National_Life_After_Death\". Slate.com.\n 240. ^ \"U.S._Civil_War_Prison_Camps_Claimed_Thousands\". National Geographic\n      News. July 1, 2003.\n 241. ^ Teresa Riordan (March 8, 2004). \"When_Necessity_Meets_Ingenuity:_Art_of\n      Restoring_What\'s_Missing\". The New York Times. The_New_York_Times\n      Company. Associated_Press. Retrieved December 23, 2013. \n 242. ^ a b Herbert Aptheker, \"Negro Casualties in the Civil War\", \"The Journal\n      of Negro History\", Vol. 32, No. 1. (January 1947).\n 243. ^ The_Economist, \"The_Civil_War:_Finally_Passing\", April 2, 2011, pp.\n      23_25.\n 244. ^ Foner_1981, p. ?.\n 245. ^ Foner_2010, p. 74.\n 246. ^ McPherson, pp. 506_8\n 247. ^ McPherson. p. 686\n 248. ^ McPherson_1988, p. 495.\n 249. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 355, 494_496, 495.\n 250. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 831_837.\n 251. ^ Winters_1963, p. 237.\n 252. ^ McPherson_1988, pp. 791_798.\n 253. ^ Lincoln\'s letter to O. H. Browning, September 22, 1861. Sentiment among\n      German_Americans was largely anti&#8211;slavery especially among Forty&#8211;\n      Eighters, resulting in hundreds of thousands of German Americans\n      volunteering to fight for the Union. \" Wittke, Carl (1952). \"Refugees of\n      Revolution\". Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania press.  \",\n      Christian B. Keller, \"Flying Dutchmen and Drunken Irishmen: The Myths and\n      Realities of Ethnic Civil War Soldiers\", Journal of Military History,\n      Vol/ 73, No. 1, January 2009, pp. 117_145; for primary sources see\n      Walter D. Kamphoefner and Wolfgang Helbich, eds., Germans in the Civil\n      War: The Letters They Wrote Home (2006). \" On the other hand, many of the\n      recent immigrants in the North viewed freed slaves as competition for\n      scarce jobs, and as the reason why the Civil War was being fought. \"\n      Baker, Kevin (March 2003). \"Violent_City\" American_Heritage. Retrieved\n      July 29, 2010. \" Due in large part to this fierce competition with free\n      blacks for labor opportunities, the poor and working class Irish\n      Catholics generally opposed emancipation. When the draft began in the\n      summer of 1863, they launched a_major_riot_in_New_York_City that was\n      suppressed by the military, as well as much smaller protests in other\n      cities. Barnet Schecter, The Devil\'s Own Work: The Civil War Draft Riots\n      and the Fight to Reconstruct America (2007), ch 6. Many Catholics in the\n      North had volunteered to fight in 1861, sending thousands of soldiers to\n      the front and taking high casualties, especially at Fredericksburg; their\n      volunteering fell off after 1862.\n 254. ^ Baker, Kevin (March 2003). \"Violent_City\" American_Heritage. Retrieved\n      July 29, 2010. \"\n 255. ^ McPherson, James in Gabor S. Boritt, ed. Lincoln, the War President pp.\n      52_54.\n 256. ^ Oates,_Stephen_B. Abraham Lincoln: The Man Behind the Myths, p. 106.\n 257. ^ \"Lincoln Letter to Greeley, August 22, 1862 \"\n 258. ^ Pulling, Sr. Anne Francis. \"Images of America: Altoona, 2001, 10.\n 259. ^ Lincoln\'s Letter to A. G. Hodges, April 4, 1864.\n 260. ^ Harper, Douglas (2003). \"SLAVERY_in_DELAWARE\". Archived from the\n      original on October 16, 2007. Retrieved October 16, 2007. \n 261. ^ \" James McPherson, The War that Never Goes Away\"\n 262. ^ Asante_2004, p. 82.\n 263. ^ Holzer_2007, p. 172&#8211;174.\n 264. ^ Murray pp. 155&#8211;159.\n 265. ^ Hans L. Trefousse, Historical Dictionary of Reconstruction (Greenwood,\n      1991) covers all the main events and leaders.\n 266. ^ Eric Foner, A Short History of Reconstruction (1990) is a brief survey\n 267. ^ Hans L Trefousse, Thaddeus Stevens: Nineteenth&#8211;Century Egalitarian\n      (2005) pp 161_238\n 268. ^ C. Vann Woodward, Reunion and Reaction: The Compromise of 1877 and the\n      End of Reconstruction (2nd ed. 1991).\n 269. ^ Joan Waugh and Gary W. Gallagher, eds. (2009), Wars within a War:\n      Controversy and Conflict over the American Civil War (U. of North\n      Carolina Press).\n 270. ^ David W. Blight, Race and Reunion : The Civil War in American Memory\n      (2001)\n 271. ^ Wilson Fallin Jr., Uplifting the People: Three Centuries of Black\n      Baptists in Alabama (2007) pp 52&#8211;53\n 272. ^ Gaines M. Foster (1988), Ghosts of the Confederacy: Defeat, the Lost\n      Cause and the Emergence of the New South, 1865_1913.\n 273. ^ Nolan, Alan T. in Gallagher, Gary W. and Alan T. Nolan, The Myth of the\n      Lost Cause and Civil War history, (2000) pp 12&#8211;19.\n 274. ^ Nolan, \'\'The Myth of the Lost Cause pp. 28&#8211;29.\n 275. ^ Charles A. Beard and Mary R. Beard, The Rise of American Civilization\n      (1927), 2:54\n 276. ^ Richard Hofstadter (2012) [1968]. Progressive_Historians. Knopf\n      Doubleday. p. 304. \n 277. ^ Gary Gallagher, Causes Won, Lost, and Forgotten: How Hollywood and\n      Popular Art Shape What We Know about the Civil War (U. of North Carolina\n      Press, 2008)\nBibliography\nMain article: Bibliography_of_the_American_Civil_War\n    * Ahlstrom, Sydney E. (1972). A_Religious_History_of_the_American_People.\n      New Haven, Connecticut: Yale University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;300&#8211;01762&#8211;5. \n    * Anderson, Bern (1989). By_Sea_And_By_River:_The_naval_history_of_the\n      Civil_War. New York, New York: Da Capo Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;306&#8211;80367&#8211;3. \n    * Asante, Molefi Kete; Mazama, Ama (2004). Encyclopedia_of_Black_Studies (1\n      ed.). Thousand Oaks, California: SAGE Publications. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;7619&#8211;2762&#8211;\n      4. \n    * Beringer, Richard E., Archer Jones, and Herman Hattaway, Why the South\n      Lost the Civil War (1986) influential analysis of factors; an abridged\n      version is The Elements of Confederate Defeat: Nationalism, War Aims, and\n      Religion (1988)\n    * Bestor, Arthur (1964). \"The American Civil War as a Constitutional\n      Crisis\". American_Historical_Review 69 (2): 327_52. JSTOR 1844986. \n    * Bolton, Charles C. (1993). Poor_Whites_of_the_Antebellum_South:_Tenants\n      and_Laborers_in_Central_North_Carolina_and_Northeast_Mississippi. Durham,\n      North Carolina: Duke University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8223&#8211;1468&#8211;4. \n    * Brunell, Miriam; Paris, Leslie (2011). The_Girls\'_History_and_Culture\n      Reader:_The_Nineteenth_Century. Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois\n      Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;252&#8211;07765&#8211;4. \n    * Canney, Donald L. (1998). Lincoln\'s_Navy:_The_Ships,_Men_and\n      Organization,_1861_65. Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;1&#8211;55750&#8211;519&#8211;4. \n    * Catton, Bruce (1960). The Civil War. New York: American Heritage\n      Distributed by Houghton Mifflin. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8281&#8211;0305&#8211;3. \n    * Chambers, John W.; Anderson, Fred (1999). The_Oxford_Companion_to\n      American_Military_History. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;507198&#8211;6. \n    * Coffman, Edward M. (1988). The_Old_Army:_A_Portrait_of_the_American_Army\n      in_Peacetime,_1784_1898. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;504555&#8211;0. \n    * Davis, William C. (1983). Stand in the Day of Battle: The Imperiled\n      Union : 1861_1865. Garden City, New York: Doubleday. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;385&#8211;\n      14895&#8211;5. \n    * Davis, William C. (2003). Look Away!: A History of the Confederate States\n      of America. New York: Free Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;7432&#8211;3499&#8211;3. \n    * Donald, David; Baker, Jean H.; Holt, Michael F. (2001). The Civil War and\n      Reconstruction. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;393&#8211;\n      97427&#8211;0. \n    * Eicher, David J. (2001). The Longest Night: A Military History of the\n      Civil War. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;684&#8211;84944&#8211;7. \n    * Fehrenbacher, Don E. (1981). Slavery,_Law,_and_Politics:_The_Dred_Scott\n      Case_in_Historical_Perspective. Oxford, New York: Oxford University\n      Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;502883&#8211;6. \n    * Fellman, Michael; Gordon, Lesley J.; Sunderland, Daniel E. (2007). This\n      Terrible War: The Civil War and its Aftermath (2 ed.). New York: Pearson.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;321&#8211;38960&#8211;2. \n    * Foner, Eric (1981). Politics_and_Ideology_in_the_Age_of_the_Civil_War.\n      Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;502926&#8211;0.\n      Retrieved April 20, 2012. \n    * Foner, Eric (2010). The_Fiery_Trial:_Abraham_Lincoln_and_American\n      Slavery. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Co. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;393&#8211;34066&#8211;2. \n    * Foote, Shelby (1974). The_Civil_War:_A_Narrative:_Volume_1:_Fort_Sumter\n      to_Perryville. New York: Vintage Books. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;394&#8211;74623&#8211;4. \n    * Frank, Joseph Allan; Reaves, George A. (2003). Seeing_the_Elephant:_Raw\n      Recruits_at_the_Battle_of_Shiloh. Urbana, Illinois: University of\n      Illinois Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;252&#8211;07126&#8211;3. \n    * Fuller, Howard J. (2008). Clad in Iron _ The American Civil War and the\n      Challenge of British Naval Power. Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute\n      Press. ISBN 978&#8211;1&#8211;59114&#8211;297&#8211;3. \n    * Gallagher, Gary W. (1999). The_Confederate_War. Cambridge, Massachusetts:\n      Harvard University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;674&#8211;16056&#8211;9. \n    * Gara, Larry. 1964. The Fugitive Slave Law: A Double Paradox in Essays on\n      the Civil War and Reconstruction, New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston,\n      1970. (originally published in Civil War History, X, No. 3, Sept 1964)\n    * Gibson, Arrell M. (1981). Oklahoma,_a_History_of_Five_Centuries. Norman,\n      Oklahoma: University of Oklahoma Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8061&#8211;1758&#8211;4. \n    * Green, Fletcher M. (2008). Constitutional_Development_in_the_South\n      Atlantic_States,_1776_1860:_A_Study_in_the_Evolution_of_Democracy.\n      Chapel Hill, North Carolina: University of North Carolina Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;1&#8211;58477&#8211;928&#8211;5. \n    * Guelzo, Allen C. (2009). Lincoln:_A_Very_Short_Introduction. Oxford, New\n      York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;536780&#8211;5. \n    * Guelzo, Allen C. (2012). Fateful Lightning: A New History of the Civil\n      War and Reconstruction. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;984328&#8211;2. \n    * Hacker, J. David (December 2011). \"A_Census&#8211;Based_Count_of_the_Civil_War\n      Dead\". Civil War History 57 (4): 307_348. doi:10.1353/cwh.2011.0061.\n      PMID 22512048. \n    * Heidler, David S.; Heidler, Jeanne T.; Coles, David J. (2002).\n      Encyclopedia of the American Civil War: A Political, Social, and Military\n      History. Santa Barbara, California: ABC&#8211;CLIO. ISBN 1&#8211;57607&#8211;382&#8211;3. \n    * Herring, George C. (2011). From_Colony_to_Superpower:_U.S._Foreign\n      Relations_since_1776. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;976553&#8211;9. \n    * Hofstadter, Richard (1938). \"The Tariff Issue on the Eve of the Civil\n      War\". American_Historical_Review 44 (1): 50_55. JSTOR 1840850. \n    * Holt, Michael F. (2005). The Fate of Their Country: Politicians, Slavery\n      Extension, and the Coming of the Civil War. New York: Hill and Wang.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8090&#8211;4439&#8211;9. \n    * Holzer, Harold; Gabbard, Sara Vaughn (2007). Lincoln_and_Freedom:\n      Slavery,_Emancipation,_and_the_Thirteenth_Amendment. Carbondale,\n      Illinois: Southern Illinois University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8093&#8211;2764&#8211;5. \n    * Huddleston, John (2002). Killing Ground: The Civil War and the Changing\n      American Landscape. Baltimore, Maryland: Johns Hopkins University Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8018&#8211;6773&#8211;6. \n    * Johannsen, Robert W. (1973). Stephen A. Douglas. New York: Oxford\n      University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;501620&#8211;8. \n    * Johnson, Timothy D. (1998). Winfield Scott: The Quest for Military Glory.\n      Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;7006&#8211;0914&#8211;7. \n    * Jones, Howard (1999). Abraham_Lincoln_and_a_New_Birth_of_Freedom:_The\n      Union_and_Slavery_in_the_Diplomacy_of_the_Civil_War. Lincoln, Nebraska:\n      University of Nebraska Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8032&#8211;2582&#8211;4. \n    * Jones, Howard (2002). Crucible_of_Power:_A_History_of_American_Foreign\n      Relations_to_1913. Wilmington, Delaware: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8420&#8211;2916&#8211;2. \n    * Katcher, Philip (2002). The History of the American Civil War 1861 _\n      1865. London: Hamlyn. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;600&#8211;60778&#8211;6. \n    * Keegan, John (2009). The American Civil War: A Military History. New\n      York: Alfred A. Knopf. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;307&#8211;26343&#8211;8. \n    * Krannawitter, Thomas L. (2008). Vindicating Lincoln : defending the\n      politics of our greatest president. Lanham, Maryland: Rowman &amp;\n      Littlefield Publishers. ISBN 0&#8211;7425&#8211;5972&#8211;6. \n    * Lipset, Seymour Martin (1960). Political Man: The Social Bases of\n      Politics. Garden City, New York: Doubleday &amp; Company, Inc. \n    * McPherson, James M. (1988). Battle_Cry_of_Freedom:_The_Civil_War_Era.\n      Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;503863&#8211;7. \n    * McPherson, James M. (1992). Ordeal By Fire : The Civil War and\n      Reconstruction (2 ed.). New York: McGraw&#8211;Hill. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;07&#8211;045842&#8211;0. \n    * McPherson, James M. (1997). For_Cause_and_Comrades:_Why_Men_Fought_in_the\n      Civil_War. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;\n      974105&#8211;2. \n    * McPherson, James M. (2007). This Mighty Scourge: Perspectives on the\n      Civil War. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;\n      539242&#8211;5. \n    * Miller, William L. (2008). President Lincoln: The Duty of a Statesman.\n      New York: Alfred A. Knopf. ISBN 1&#8211;4000&#8211;4103&#8211;1. \n    * Thornton, Mark; Ekelund, Robert Burton (2004). Tariffs, Blockades, and\n      Inflation: The Economics of the Civil War. Rowman &amp; Littlefield. \n    * Murray, Robert Bruce. Legal Cases of the Civil War. (2003) ISBN_0&#8211;8117&#8211;\n      0059&#8211;3\n    * Murray, Williamson; Bernstein, Alvin; Knox, MacGregor (1996). The_Making\n      of_Strategy:_Rulers,_States,_and_War. Cabmbridge, New York: Cambridge\n      University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;521&#8211;56627&#8211;8. \n    * Neely, Mark (1993). Confederate_Bastille:_Jefferson_Davis_and_Civil\n      Liberties. Milwaukee, Wisconsin: Marquette University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;\n      87462&#8211;325&#8211;3. \n    * Nelson, James L. (2005). Reign_of_Iron:_The_Story_of_the_First_Battling\n      Ironclads,_the_Monitor_and_the_Merrimack. New York: HarperCollins.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;06&#8211;052404&#8211;3. \n    * Nevins,_Allan. Ordeal_of_the_Union, an 8&#8211;volume set (1947_1971). the\n      most detailed political, economic and military narrative; by Pulitzer\n      Prize winner\n          o 1. Fruits of Manifest Destiny, 1847_1852; 2. A House Dividing,\n            1852_1857; 3. Douglas, Buchanan, and Party Chaos, 1857_1859; 4.\n            Prologue to Civil War, 1859_1861; vol. 5_8 have the series\n            title \"War for the Union\"; 5. The Improvised War, 1861_1862; 6.\n            War Becomes Revolution, 1862_1863; 7. The Organized War,\n            1863_1864; 8. The Organized War to Victory, 1864_1865\n    * Olsen, Christopher J. (2002). Political_Culture_and_Secession_in\n      Mississippi:_Masculinity,_Honor,_and_the_Antiparty_Tradition,\n      1830_1860. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;19&#8211;\n      516097&#8211;0. \n    * Perman, Michael; Taylor, Amy M. (2010). Major_Problems_in_the_Civil_War\n      and_Reconstruction:_Documents_and_Essays (3 ed.). Boston, Massachusetts:\n      Wadsworth, Cengage Learning. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;618&#8211;87520&#8211;7. \n    * Potter, David M. (1962). \"The Historian\'s Use of Nationalism and Vice\n      Versa\". American_Historical_Review 67 (4): 924_950. JSTOR 1845246. \n    * Potter, David M.; Fehrenbacher, Don E. (1976). The Impending Crisis,\n      1848_1861. New York: Harper &amp; Row. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;06&#8211;013403&#8211;7. \n    * Quarstein, John V. (1999). The Battle of the Ironclads. Arcadia\n      Publishing. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;7385&#8211;0113&#8211;0. \n    * Rhodes, John Ford (1917). History_of_the_Civil_War,_1861_1865. New\n      York: The Macmillan Company. \n    * Richards, Leonard L. (2000). The_Slave_Power:_The_Free_North_and_Southern\n      Domination,_1780_1860. Baton Rouge, Louisiana: Louisiana State\n      University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8071&#8211;2600&#8211;4. \n    * Richter, William L. (2009). The_A_to_Z_of_the_Civil_War_and\n      Reconstruction. Lanham: Scarecrow Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8108&#8211;6336&#8211;1. \n    * Russell, Robert R. (1966). \"Constitutional Doctrines with Regard to\n      Slavery in Territories\". Journal_of_Southern_History 32 (4): 466_486.\n      doi:10.2307/2204926. JSTOR 2204926. \n    * Schott, Thomas E. (1996). Alexander H. Stephens of Georgia: A Biography.\n      Baton Rouge, Louisiana: Louisiana State University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;\n      8071&#8211;2106&#8211;1. \n    * Schouler, William (1899). The_Civil_War_(History_of_the_United_States_of\n      America_Under_the_Constitution,_Volume_VI_1861_1865). Dodd, Mead &amp;\n      Company. ASIN B00088INOY. \n    * Stampp, Kenneth M. (1990). America in 1857: A Nation on the Brink.\n      Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0&#8211;19&#8211;503902&#8211;5. \n    * Symonds, Craig L.; Clipson, William J. (2001). The_Naval_Institute\n      Historical_Atlas_of_the_U.S._Navy. Naval Institute Press. ISBN 978&#8211;1&#8211;\n      55750&#8211;984&#8211;0. \n    * Tucker, Spencer C.; Pierpaoli, Paul G.; White, William E. (2011). The\n      Civil_War_Naval_Encyclopedia. Santa Barbara, California: ABC&#8211;CLIO.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;1&#8211;59884&#8211;338&#8211;5. \n    * Varon, Elizabeth R. (2008). Disunion!: The Coming of the American Civil\n      War, 1789_1859. Chapel Hill, North Carolina: University of North\n      Carolina Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8078&#8211;3232&#8211;5. \n    * Vinovskis, Maris (1990). Toward_a_Social_History_of_the_American_Civil\n      War:_Exploratory_Essays. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press.\n      ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;521&#8211;39559&#8211;5. \n    * Ward, Geoffrey R. (1990). The Civil War: An Illustrated History. New\n      York: Alfred A. Knopf. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;394&#8211;56285&#8211;8. \n    * Weeks, William E. (2013). The_New_Cambridge_History_of_American_Foreign\n      Relations. Cambridge, New York: Cambridge University Press. ISBN 978&#8211;1&#8211;\n      107&#8211;00590&#8211;7. \n    * Weigley, Frank Russell (2004). A_Great_Civil_War:_A_Military_and\n      Political_History,_1861_1865. Bloomington, Indiana: Indiana University\n      Press. ISBN 0&#8211;253&#8211;33738&#8211;0. \n    * Welles, Gideon (1865). Secretary_of_the_Navy\'s_Report. 37_38. American\n      Seamen\'s Friend Society. \n    * Winters, John D. (1963). The_Civil_War_in_Louisiana. Baton Rouge,\n      Louisiana: Louisiana_State_University_Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;8071&#8211;0834&#8211;5. \n    * Woodworth, Steven E. (1996). American Civil War: A Handbook of Literature\n      and Research. Wesport, Connecticut: Greenwood Press. ISBN 978&#8211;0&#8211;313&#8211;\n      29019&#8211;0. \n\n<u> Further reading \n</u>\n\n    * Gugliotta, Guy. New_Estimate_Raises_Civil_War_Death_Toll, The_New_York\n      Times, April 3, 2012, pg. D1 (of the New York edition), and April 2, 2012\n      on NYTimes.com. Retrieved 2012&#8211;04&#8211;03 online.\n    * Bibliography_of_American_Civil_War_naval_history\n    *  Chisholm, Hugh, ed. (1911). \"American_Civil_War\". EncyclopÃ¦dia\n      Britannica (11th ed.). Cambridge University Press. \n\n</string>
</resources>
